Your source for Orthodox books, podcasts, videos, and more, we are ancient faith ministries.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him.
And they will pray.
praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48 verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to
see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
What do we put?
permeate everyday life with spiritual presence.
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung,
host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers,
demon dodgers, and hemorrhors of homunculi.
You are listening to Lord of Spirit's pie.
guest. My co-host, Father Stephen D'Young, is with me from Lafayette Louisiana, and I am
Father Andrew Stephen Damick in Emeas, Pennsylvania, in the beautiful Lehigh Valley. And we are
live. So, and if you are listening to us live, you can call us at 855-237-2346, and you
could talk to us. We're going to get your calls in the second half of the show, and our
very own Matroska Trudy will be taking those calls.
before the commercial.
Yeah, yeah.
That new station identification.
Right, yes, right before our the voice of truthy. Yeah. Yeah. Is we her new preferred pronoun?
Wow, I don't want to commit any microaggressions while we're reporting
I thought I'd clarify that before we go live. Oh, it's the editorial we never mind. Oh, okay
Yes, okay. Okay. Thank you for cleaning that up
So this episode this episode is sponsored by the orthodox studies institute at St. Constantine college
which exists to advance the study and application of Orthodox Christianity and faithfulness to holy tradition.
OSI is currently offering a live online course on the book of Enoch taught by our very own.
Father Stephen Diagn. The course is underway, but by popular demand OSI has reopened registration
and you can catch up on the recordings of earlier classes and participate in the live classes
is going forward. So to learn more and to register, go to orthodoxstudies.org slash
LOS registration is now open also for OSI's next course, which is Holy Women of Byzantium
and that's going to begin in October.
So again, go to orthodoxstudies.org slash LOS to learn more about the ENOC course.
And on Tuesday night, they participate, described this course as Lord of Spirits in a Sutant
high. Although I do not, in fact, wear a suit and tie.
What did you even own a suit and tie? I own a suit. I
Don't think I own a tie anymore. I've been a priest for more than 15 years. I think I'd no longer own a tie. Yeah
So well in the long ago times there was something called the Stone Age and this is generally divided into the
Paleolithic
Mesolithic and Neolithic periods which just means old middle and new people
So it is this last period from which
which archaeology tells us something about ancient religion.
But what does this have to do with Christianity?
And how should we understand the continuity of religion from that most ancient of detectable
prehistory to the Orthodox Christianity of our own day?
And we should probably start with asking what religion is though.
So I'm assuming everybody agrees on what religion is?
Pretty much.
Oh, that's the first half has gone.
Yeah.
you're old.
Oh, well, also watching to know I don't know if you actually prepared for this evening.
I did by eating my own version of the paleo diet today. Nice. So for lunch, I had a pound of
bacon and two fingers of scotch. I said, I had breakfast for dinner, which feels pretty, pretty
paleo. Well, it depends on what kind of breakfast. We're talking to steak and eggs or eggs and sausage.
Yeah, that's fair. Yeah. Yeah. Was it the chief sausage with lots of filler?
No, no, this was this actually comes from a farm out in western Pennsylvania.
Okay. Okay. So yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Thank you very much.
So, yeah. So we are, there was kind of a confluence of Lord of Spirit's tropes for tonight's episode.
Because on one hand, we like to start episodes in the Stone Age.
But on the other hand, our topic tonight is the Stone Age and everyone knows we don't
get to our topic until the third half.
Waves of disappointment are now flowing through YouTube.
Yes.
Right.
Which one of those would take effect?
Well, the latter.
So fair warning, we will, as typical, get to our actual topic in the third half.
But until then, we will be laying groundwork.
Yeah.
And as comic books, Star Trek, whatever else.
as father Andrew alluded, we're going to start by talking about what religion is anyway.
Right. Because you say the term religion and everybody kind of thinks they know what that means.
But if you press people about what that means, often people can't tell you exactly what that means.
in the sense of trying to give a definition, trying to say, okay, this is what religion is.
Yeah, especially something that's gonna fit all of the things that we regard as being
religions as being religious, but then also exclude all the things that we generally
don't think of as being religious.
So that's actually a lot trickier, right, than it sounds.
And even the people who talk about religion the most and by that I mean atheists on the
internet can't come up with a good definition of what religion is and therefore we could safely
say.
folks don't know what they're talking about. But and and a lot of these arguments, you'll
hear these sort of broad statements from the Fedora gang saying things like, you know,
while religion is responsible for all the war hate bad things expired lunch meat in the
world. Right? Like, uh,
And it's just religion if we just get rid of religion
Right then we live in this beautiful utopia right of wonder and by enlightenment
Wow, yeah, and by this I mean, you know everyone from edgy teens to
Richard Dawkins and Sam Harris
It's true. I mean it's true. Make these kind of broad unsupported. Yeah, frankly childish statements
so
And again, when pressed, right?
What's religion and what isn't?
Yeah. So I remember back in the late Neolithic era
when you and I were undergrads,
which I know for you like lasted a good two months,
whatever.
It was a little less than three calendar years.
There we go.
Did you start your undergrad when you were like 16
or something like that?
Is that right?
Yeah.
a little bit later for me.
Yeah, I mean, I remember I took, I actually took a class in philosophy of science and the
whole beginning of the class was the professor essentially eviscerating every definition
that a student could come up with that said religion is on this side and science is on this
side.
And as I told you earlier today, I don't remember the particulars of that class because
again it was in the late Neolithic period, but um
I did come away with a very beautiful sense of, okay,
this game is not like what the Fedora clan,
make it out to be.
Right.
Although we're edgy atheists in the early 90s
wearing Fedoras, they're really kind of trilby's,
actually, I think, not actual Fedoras.
Yeah, well, yeah, trying to think the atheist I knew.
See, those were the old atheists, right?
The guys I'm describing are the quote unquote new atheists.
and knew it.
Yeah, that's true at old atheists were just a better class of atheists
Right, I mean like especially if you go real old school like you're Nietzsche you're
Oh, yeah, that guy actually didn't believe in things. Yes
Right like there were some top level atheists, you know back in the late 19th and early 20th century
You know and then you know
Really, I think the first like edge lord publicity seeking
atheist who like public atheist to sell books and file law knowing nuisance lawsuits was
Madeline Murio hair. Oh yes. Remember her. Oh yes. Yes indeed. Who had an interesting
personal life. But yeah, she was on Phil Donahue show talking about how it doesn't exist
which was a super edgy thing to do even on Phil Donahue's show, like in the evenings.
Wow.
So yeah, a lot of atheists were in the closet then at least in the US.
I think in Europe they were more free to, you know, but they also didn't have the same
chip on their shoulder in Europe, I think.
I think they just, in Europe, they just weren't religious.
Yeah, I mean, you'll need to badger anyone about it.
A lot of the new atheist stuff was really not about like presenting any kind of new or
better arguments.
It was like, okay, let's all point and laugh, you know, is, is, uh, honestly, honestly,
Yes, I don't have a religion, but all I'm going to do every day is think about and post about religion. Yeah
Yes, so yeah, but whatever religion is yeah, whatever exactly whatever whatever that you know sort of is
you know and
If you ever tried to argue with those people which I did in the early days of the internet when the system of tubes had just been connected
before I realized it was pointless.
You would get these interesting things, you know, because they would say things like well
non-religious people never go and murder religious people for being religious and you'd bring up say, you know,
Stalin, Mao, Pol Pot, right?
Lenin, you know, I
would get two responses. One, I literally had an atheist once tell me that
Lenin's League of the militant godless was not a militant atheist organization
which was fascinating, right?
Doesn't do what it says on the tin.
Yeah, exactly.
To shame.
And, but more common was, they would say that communism
or Marxism is a religion.
Wow.
Right, so any bad ideology that they don't like,
even if it was just as atheistic as them,
they would try and say, well, that ideology is a religion
or is religion.
So basically everything except science as they understand it.
And of course, you know, they've taken like three science classes at high school.
So, but, yeah.
So even there they would get used in a slippery way in the other direction.
Right?
And there were Christian apologists doing that too.
Josh McDowell at one point published a book called Secular Religions.
Oh man.
where he described like secular humanism and...
communism and fascism as religions. Yeah. So, you know, that's not that's not everything
I don't like is religion. That was more in his case, I think he was trying to argue
that just everybody is religious, like people won't admit it. I mean, that's basically
kind of valid on the surface. So yeah, so then you argue, well, okay, you're a whatever.
So that's really your religion and Christianity's better than that one.
Right, I think...
which is was the approach he was trying to take at that point.
So where does the word religion come from?
Because it's a relative late-comer to English, but it's developed from a Latin word.
Yeah, it's only from the 13th, early 13th century in English, and I don't have the jingle to play.
Sorry everybody. Which is, I'm not going to do a whole Latin word.
Yeah, exactly, even a Latin word. And when it comes into English, it's literally from day one,
It's being used to describe people who live in a monastery.
Yes, religious.
Yeah, right.
Which sounds like a funny way of using it now, especially Catholics talk about the religious.
By that they mean monks and nuns and so forth.
But that is the oldest use of it in English is that.
But the idea is that they're bound to this particular life, right?
right, which is probably where the Latin red legio comes from.
Yeah, people are you about this because you know journal articles. Yeah, but the majority opinion
a large majority opinion is that it comes from it's the prefix re in front of Leo, which is
the same word as ligature, which means to tie or bind something. And in this case the re is an
intensifier. Yeah. Yeah. So it's it's something that binds something together and that that
fits right with how religion is used. For example, as we've talked about a lot on the show,
one of the main purposes of religious ritual in general is to bind together groups of people
to maintain, establish, reestablish when broken bonds within a community and between a community
and it's God or God's. So that seems a very...
right.
Right.
Apt.
A origin for the term, even if we can't 100% prove it.
Now before that though, right, we start seeing it used in Latin very early in Latin literature.
So Cicero uses it though in a weird way.
by current standards.
But I mean, later on Augustine, St. Augustine uses it.
I mean, it's in Latin.
It is a Latin term.
I'll be one whose meaning shifts over time like all terms.
Before that though, you're talking about various words
that we now translate with some version of piety,
which is based on a different Latin word.
Right, so you're not going to find
Greek literature, for example, there's not really a word for religious. Right? There are
some, sometimes people will translate certain Greek words like in the New Testament as religious,
but really if they translate those words consistently, consistently everywhere they translate
them, it ends up being something like pious piety. Right. Yeah. Which is like like pious
in Latin is sort of like, beautiful.
basically. Right, right. And so in a party that's coming, coming to
Greek semisd which has a similar idea, the idea is that this is, this is an
ethical, piety is an ethical quality. Right. So we think of what you're
piety or religiosity as this sort of accessory that someone may or may not
have. Right? They're like, yeah.
He's very pious. Yeah, and then some people are less pious and some people aren't at all, right?
But it was considered a sort of ethical virtue
Right alongside things like courage and honor and
Dealing justly right what made you a good person part of that was
Piety particularly in the Roman sphere, which is why we get
word, piety to translate it. It was, you know, a sense of honoring all of your duties. Yeah.
I mean, just read, read the in the it. If you need to know what the Roman idea of piety
is, like in this is he is the pie as guy in in Roman legend. Whereas in, um, in, uh, Greek
circles it was more seen as a
another way in which a great man could display his excellence. But Aristotle, for example,
will argue that piety like everything is a mean between two extremes. So someone can, for
Aristotle, be two pious. I think religious extremists, I guess. I don't know. Sacrificing one
too many goats. Right well.
I don't know. I think it would more be I think for him, you'd probably be talking about someone who was like overly obsessed with auger or something, right?
Like, yeah, yeah, yeah, to the point that it detracted from their life or something. Right.
I've met people like that. That's augers mostly on the internet. People have something with auger. Yeah.
Yeah.
But so like when St. Paul says to the people of Athens, it's translated out, but I see that
you're...
very religious, right? He's talking about the fact that he sees all these idols and all
these shrines, right? He says, it means I see you take these things very seriously. Yeah.
Right. This is something you're you've invested time and effort as a community in, right?
This is something that is of concern to you, right? And so they would have received that
is a complement.
Right. Like I see that you are very courageous or I see that you are very just right. It's kind of
Yeah, so
that
You know, it's important to kind of understand this idea of religion or religiosity of the ancient world
But that doesn't really help us define religion too much
No, because I mean we're pointing it a
Certain set of be well a various sets of behaviors
I shouldn't say certain set of behaviors various sets of behaviors and we're calling all that stuff
Really
Right, right. We're talking about some property of a human who has some dutifulness
Right or diligence about some. Yeah. I mean within Greek paganism. It's duty to the gods
Yeah, but that's
That's not the only religion in the world and that could take various forms. Oh, yeah various times and various places that are radically different right
So
We've talked before.
the show about how our now our definition of religion as we think about it as modern
post and like it be like me people which we all are whether we like it or not is very
much tied up with the concept of religions or that there's such a thing as a religion.
Right.
There are these various individual religions out there.
And then if we're going to talk about religion in general, right, then like, uh,
religion is the genus and then there are all these species right of religions
with underneath that. With groupings underneath those yeah. And that is a very
new way of thinking. So the idea of a religion really starts being spoken over
the 17th century.
Like when ancient people encountered people that we would regard as being from a different religion
They would I mean they could certainly see that there's a difference between them, right? But it was more like
These are your ways these are our ways you serve those gods. We serve these gods
Yeah, you know, that was the way that they conceived it. It wasn't like oh, I have this religion and you have that religion
Yes, I practiced Greek paganism and you practice, you know
Indian beggar
Right? Or Persian paganism or Egyptian paganism, right? Because that's not how they thought of it, right?
It was those are your gods. These are my gods. Your gods want you to do XYZ for them. My gods want me to do XYZ for me, right?
And there was a little bit of our gods are better than your gods.
Sure, especially from the Greeks.
Because the Greeks even though their gods were originally Therium or for example,
are always accusing Egyptians and Indians of worshiping animals. This proves that our religion is
more refined, but what they meant by that was we understand the divine better than they do.
Yeah. Not we have a different religion and our religion is better than theirs and we want to
try to convert them to ours. Yeah, that was, that was, that was not a thing, right? But so the pre-requisite
in thought for talking about a religion is that there has to be a concept of religion in which religion
is an element of human life or human culture that is separable from other elements of human life
and human culture. And this is how we're used to thinking about it as modern people. So you have
you're really
religion, that's like one basket, you have your politics, that's another basket.
You have your, you know, ethnic identity, that's another basket, right?
And there may be connections between these baskets.
In fact, people will probably argue all of these are connected, but they really are different
baskets, right?
And especially when you look at, after the 30 years war in Europe, the 30 years of the
30 years war wrecks Europe, kills like a third of the people.
And then after the 30 years war, right,
and Catholics and Protestants have finished
for the time being killing each other
and don't want to kill each other anymore.
And they take a break from killing
like Jewish people and other minorities,
short break, but, right?
They say to prevent this from happening again.
We need to reconceive of what binds us together as a people.
Yeah, this sort of idea of kind of the secular space on some level is born.
Right.
By this identity of being, you know,
Prussian or something like that, you know, that is above your quote-unquote religion.
Right.
And so it shifts to nationalism.
It shifts to nationalism.
Instead of, you know, the center of my identity,
or someone's identity being a Roman Catholic,
it becomes they are a Frenchman.
Right. And so someone can be a Frenchman
and be Roman Catholic, someone can be a Frenchman
and be Jewish, someone can be a Frenchman and be Protestant.
Right. They had to reconsider this so that,
right, they didn't have to, you know,
try and kill all the Protestants, right?
Or in Protestant countries, kill all the Roman Catholics.
Right.
It's those identity forms and this is you could definitely see this
Kind of thinking at the forefront in the United States today
Oh totally yeah Americans first of all yeah, and then we have all kinds of different religions and different practices and different cultures
But we're all Americans and that's what's really important right
and
What that does is right that that shift of identity then
and relativizes religions.
cultures, political views, all of these other things, ethical views, right, and turns
them into these baskets, these ancillary baskets, into which different things can be put.
Yeah, and you get this idea that religion can be a private matter, right?
That kind of thing.
So you have this religion socket, right, and you can plug all these different things
in the socket.
And once you have that idea that it's a socket with different things you can plug into
the socket then all of those.
potential plugins, right, get referred to as religions, right, as religions. And so that
means, and it was mainly the Europeans doing this. This means that, for example, we're going
to talk about a religion Hinduism.
talk about it like it's an organized religion. Right? And for people who don't know, the
term Hinduism is just a catch-all. It literally means the religion of the people of the Indus
River Valley. Yeah, it's not a religion. Yeah, it's just sort of, it's a whole big collection
of traditions of over a billion people, you know, most of which are super local. Yeah, yeah.
And so you get and we can say this.
same thing, right, about, I mean, we don't think of it this way, but you could say the same thing about Greek religion.
Yeah, right. We've kind of thrown everything into this big paganism pile, right? But,
but the Hinduism is a religion, Buddhism is a religion, right? And then, you know, the Europeans taxonomize like
as if there are denominations of Buddhism.
that had split off or something as if it was Protestantism.
Right.
Yeah.
There's Zen Buddhism, man.
There's Theravada Buddhism and there's, you know.
And so all these things just sort of get normalized.
And then once you have that, right?
So once we have this idea that there are these different religions that could all be sort
of hooked up or that people could choose between.
You get the whole
concept of comparative religions. Right? And the problem with comparative religion, the
idea of comparative religion is not that, you know, you can't compare things. You can compare
any two things. Sure. You can compare a raven in a writing desk. You can compare chalk and
cheese. Right? There are no two things that you cannot compare to one another. The problem
is that in order to compare things
You have to have some kind of structure in order to perceive commonalities.
So if I was going to write an essay comparing chalk and cheese,
I would have to try to find things that chalk and cheese have in common.
That's tricky, right?
But in order to do that, I'd have to do a couple things.
Number one, I would probably have to make those
comparison's really broad and not detailed, right? Like most chalk is yellow or white, most
cheese is yellow or white, right? Which is sort of so vague, it doesn't tell you anything
about chalk or anything about cheese really, right? So how helpful is that comparison at
that point right because it's so vague so that's the first thing that happens.
or you make a comparison in some way that sort of does a little violence to either chalk
or cheese.
You can bite off a piece of chalk and you can bite off a piece of cheese.
Many of us out there have done so.
Technically, technically true.
But biting off a piece of chalk and biting off a piece of cheese are two fundamentally different
experiences.
Alright.
And so again, you're kind of having to fudge a little on the side of the chalk, right,
in order to make this comparison.
And so again, how helpful or useful is that comparison at this point?
And so this is what you find with comparative religion, right?
You find a lot of square pegs getting beaten into round holes.
I think I've mentioned this before on the show.
You see this, you see this a lot around.
Christmas and around Paska, around Nativity and around Paska.
Here's all the ways that the story of Jesus is ripped off from
fill in the blank pagans.
Yes.
First of all, most of them are even true.
You get this myth, it's had 12 Disciple stuff.
There's literally citation needed.
should need it. Like yeah, making there is no source for that, right?
But even the ones that are true, right, like you'll get the list of people who had a virgin birth.
Right. And invariably when you get that, one of the people on the list is Adonis.
Right. And for those who don't know, the way Adonis was born was, Zeus was wandering around one day
on his way to probably commit sex crimes.
and as Zeus does, as is his want.
And he decides to pleasure himself.
Okay.
And from the place where he does that, a tree grows.
Yeah.
And then,
I should get a parental warning at the beginning
of this episode.
Maybe, I don't know.
I think those were fake enough terms.
Yeah.
And so then years later, a young woman is sitting
to the tree, a piece of...
Fruit falls off of the tree of lands at her lap and she gets pregnant and gives birth to a donus.
And that's just like in the New Testament, right? Yes, that is exactly like Luke two.
Like you can clearly see how how
St. Luke stole that to describe Jesus for it. Right.
So you see what I'm saying? This is an example, right? We go so vague.
Right.
Someone who is born without their parents having participated in...
in conjugal relations.
Right?
And then we may say, oh, see, look, Jesus and Adonis, right?
But then how helpful is that comparison
when you actually read the two stories?
Yeah.
Right?
It doesn't do justice to either of the two stories.
And it just is kind of absurd.
But this is because we've got,
well, Christianity is a religion.
And Greek paganism is a religion.
Right?
So...
We could sort of chart out and see, you know, how they're similar.
This also, and relatedly, this is where you start getting the sort of taxonomies of religion.
And the taxonomies of religion kind of take two forms.
One form is, well, okay, we're going to group things together that we've decided are similar.
Right, so you get these big
categories like monotheism, which again, it's in the 17th century when people start using that word in
Europe. Yeah, see episode one of the Lord. Yeah, it's podcast. Even though the Greek words, monos and
theros, right? So the church fathers could have talked about monotheism all day if they wanted to, but
they didn't use the term. There's monotheism and there's polytheism. Right. So here's two categories.
and all the religions that...
We're gonna say the sake of argument only have one God
We're gonna put the monotheism category like what do you do with the hurrah Mazda? What do you do anyway?
And then all these other pagan religions where they talk about lots of gods
We're gonna put those over the the polytheism category, right?
And you start getting these groupings like oh the Abrahamic religions. Yeah, right that somehow involves
Abraham
Right, I'll get grouped.
over here, right? And you sort of group together things that you think are alike, right?
But again, your decision that they're alike is based on these sort of bad awkward comparisons,
in a lot of cases. And then also, you start getting the taxonomies, which lead inevitably
to the 19th century German conclusion that all of human religion is culminated in 19th century German
and Lutheranism.
I feel like I've heard that somewhere before.
Because, you know, starting with the most primitive, you know, religion, the most primitive
polytheism, right, in their taxonomies, the crudest, most idolatrous, you know, polytheism,
working their way up to the stately cadence of the German corral, right?
And so once we have these ideas, discrete religions, we could chart them into this evolutionary
work of, you know, religion becoming more and more refined until it ineffably leads to us
whoever us is. I guess earlier the show Trudy is the us. Trudy is the height of all the
Trudy is the power development apparently. Self proclaimed, that's what's crazy.
That's descriptive. All that we just talked about is kind of descriptive, right?
In terms of what has happened and how the term religion and religions
came into use and are used, that doesn't really help us understand what religion is though, right? Because
we as we just talked about a lot of the fruit of that of those taxonomies and comparative religion are
unhelpful and
phony
Do
violence to the actual religious expressions that they're talking about.
Yeah. And I mean, and just to kind of like,
like sometimes people say things like, well, religion is about God, but there are religions
that don't have any kind of God figure or, you know, religion is about...
In the way we think of God, yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
They don't, you know, religion is about spiritual things.
Well, you know, like...
I mean, not that you should ever take Scientology seriously and never take it seriously.
I mean, it does seriously bad things, but you should not take it as a religion.
Yeah, definitely never give the money.
But their whole deal is sort of using this kind of scientific...
Science fiction.
Yeah, to measure things.
The whole thing is that they're a kind of a non-spiritual religion.
Yeah.
Anyway, let me tell you, as somebody who's read all 10 volumes of Mission Earth, Elrond
Hubbard was not even a good sci-fi author.
Why did you do that?
That I need to know because I was really bored one summer.
Like really bored in the radio.
And they had all of them at the local library.
Wow.
I remember they ads for Dianetics in the 1980s, you know, like with the volcano and all
that kind of stuff, dionetics.
Yeah, I mean, you're 14 years old, you know, you could only afford so many comic books to read and your judgment is not that great at 14 and it's just like I'm your read sci-fi novels and you know, you've gone through the classes, you've gone through Ray Bradbury, you've gone through Isaac Asimov, you're running out of stuff, right?
There's a long summer yawning out ahead of you.
What are you to do?
Summer Father's DNA hit rock bottom.
Yeah, you say whatever and buy books.
six of Mission Earth Trust me.
You're like, why am I reading this?
This is horrible.
But it is a 14 year old.
But now your six books in at a 10.
60% is a failing grade, right?
Like, you can't just stop now if you were a petty
and a hell of a pound.
If you win the Elron Hubbard novels,
aren't you failing it life?
I don't know.
I don't know, but I finished them.
And uh, I am high...
Even if you like bad sci-fi, I am not recommending them because they are in places literally pornographic.
Yeah, they're not so bad. They're just so bad. They're bad.
Yeah, they're just bad.
Like Elrond Hoverd was clearly just a giant, weird, dysfunctional id.
Like pouring out his weirdest and deepest thoughts and fantasies onto a page.
Could it be a Thedans?
Yeah, so
Yeah. But technically there are religion I guess. They have five or one C3 status I think
still. Yeah. Yeah. That's all the countries are not aware of the truth. Yeah. Yeah.
nicer country's perhaps.
So, there's also a major pit-
fall here that we have to avoid as we're trying to come up with some kind of working definition
of what religion is, right? And that pitfall is one that almost everyone falls into when
they start talking about that. This and that is that they see religion in general in terms
of their own religious background. Yeah, they define other religions to be like whatever
they're used to but just sort of trade out some details. Right. Right.
And so this leads to innumerable understandings, misunderstandings.
If you've ever had serious conversations with someone of another religion, even if we're
talking about religious stuff, that at one point was very close, like trying to talk to
an orthodox Jewish person, right?
One of the big obstacles is going to be that they're going to understand Christianity through
the lens of rabbinical Judaism.
And you, if you're a Christian...
and are going to kind of understand Judaism
through the lens of Christianity.
Yeah, like one really common thing, for instance,
is especially, frankly, within Protestantism,
there's this idea of defining religion
in terms of beliefs, right?
And it's funny, I remember, this isn't true anymore,
but I remember the day that I discovered
the Facebook was Protestant, because it said
you could define your religious views.
I could have those views.
views. These are my views. Yeah. Yeah. But you'll see a lot of that even in Old
textbook, right? Here are the core beliefs or core tenets of Hinduism. Here are
the core tenets of Islam. Yeah. Or even the idea that like, well, everybody's
trying to get salvation. And they just have different ideas about how you get
there. I'm like, no, they're not. The goals of different religions are very
different from each other. Yeah. You know, a colleague at salvation, you have to do
one of those really brah
comparisons when you're looping in things that are very unlike. Yeah. And calling them the same. Yeah.
Like that. Like Hindu Yogan salvation for him is being released from, you know, embodied
selfhood and being coming not only disembodied, but no longer a self. That's, quote unquote,
salvation within that context. That is a very different goal than your local Baptist and what he's
He's trying to cheat when he goes to church on Sunday.
Especially if he knows about the bottom.
to leave resurrection. Right. He's looking forward to eternal life. Yeah. They're kind of opposites.
Yeah. Yeah. And the whole beliefs thing, right? Again, that's, you know, oh, well, if you believe
X Y Z boom, you're a Hindu. No, you're not. Right? That's you believe X Y Z. Oh, now you're a member
of Shinto? No, you're not. Sorry.
basement dwelling weep right just because you read some stuff about Japan that decided you wanted to be shinto that doesn't make you shinto
Right is not and you know
Just because you read one book about highly salicy you are not a rastafarian now
It's not just a question of you know, I think these are good ideas therefore I am now a blank
Yeah.
And yeah, you also get...
you know, in these discussions, you'll see especially again from, and when we say, we're
not just saying, oh, Protestants do this. We're saying people from a Protestant religious
background, people who live in Protestant countries, even if they're not religious, right,
tend to think about religion in these ways, because it's sort of the majority religion
of their country, right? They'll talk about, oh, these are the sacred texts, right? So
like Christians have the Bible.
Jewish people just have the Old Testament, and Muslims have the Quran, and Hindus have like
the Vedas or the Bhagavad Gita or something.
As if these texts and daoists have the Daoji Ching, right?
These books all just function the same way in all of these quote-unquote religions, that
the Bible functions for...
an American evangelical Protestant, right in their mind.
And this is like, no, right? Of course not. And it's one of the most amazing things in the world.
On the interwebs, right? And you can see this any day of the week. If you watch an atheist arguing
with the Christian, right? The atheist will take...
like the most fundamentalist possible literal interpretation of every verse of scripture.
Yes.
Right. And the Christian of whatever stripe arguing with him will desperately try to explain,
like, look, no one reads it that way. Right. Like that's not right. No one,
things that means that no one reads it that way, right. And get super frustrated. But then if
that same Christian goes and talks to a Muslim, he will take the most fundamentalist possible
literal interpretation of any
the verse of the Quran. Yeah.
Well, the Muslim tries to explain to everybody reads it that way. Right?
And it's because both that Christian and that atheist are Americans.
And so evangelical Christianity is what's around them.
Yeah, I mean, so they just assume that that's how everyone reads their sacred text.
And also just the intellectual habit of reductionism.
Yeah. You know,
which is a bad habit people.
Yes, yeah.
And all the other side to be fair, so they can't say, I mean, the US is a majority Protestant
and majority evangelical Protestant country, right?
But you'll see this sometimes with high church Protestants and Roman Catholics and even some
Orthodox people, where they'll talk about other religions in terms of like hierarchical
structures, right?
Like they try to make the Dalai Lama like the Pope of Buddhism or something.
I did notice one time
So maybe this is how it works, that I actually did the little survey of media, of media
that's talking about religion.
And I found out that at least American media uses the phrase his holiness more often for
the Dalai Lama than they do for the Pope.
And I was like, that's really kind of interesting.
They have to, they're using this indirect honorific for, you know, this religious
leader and not for the one who's actually probably more familiar for using that title.
It's pretty funny.
I don't know.
I think Protestant America is more deeply anti-Catholic.
They are deeply anti-Buddhist.
Yeah.
Absolutely.
Plus you have the whole liberal.
Well, that's another culture.
Yes.
Right.
That's how they call him.
Yeah.
Whereas most popes are white people.
Yeah, that's...
Yeah, so there are all kinds of those misunderstandings, right?
And they go in always.
Okay, so what can we come up with as a definition of religion that is both workable, right?
Meaning there aren't obvious massive flaws in it, right?
obvious massive flaws would be.
exclude some things that are obviously religious or include some things that obviously aren't.
Yeah, like the classic example would be saying, well, religion is about how you relate to God
or gods and people saying, okay, well, then Buddhism is not a religion because it's sort of
non-theistic. Therefore, it's a philosophy. But yeah, I mean, take a look at any kind of Buddhist practice,
people and I don't mean
burn an instant man I don't mean
California but
Okay, I mean, I mean Buddhism and where it's native and that is clearly a religion just look at it. Just look at it. Yes. Yes, Richard Gears pool parties are not actual Buddhist rituals.
I know there's probably a lot of disappointed people out there that just I know what I know what like that means I've never been to church.
So um, but also a working definition.
meaning a definition that's actually useful for something.
That's not like so vague in some way in order to not transgress those limits.
There's nothing to be derived from it.
So here's what we're proposing tonight.
It's sort of a working and workable definition of religion.
that religion is a way of being in the world.
That encompasses all levels of reality and expresses itself in practices
Okay
So there's three sort of key parts there yeah, right
The first one is talking about a way of being in the world right
because
And the reason it's phrased that way is that
that we want to get away from the idea of
thought or ideas or beliefs, right? That could be included in a way of being in
the world, but sort of isn't required, right? So a way of being in the world can
include, right, who you think God is or a relationship you believe you have with
that Rhaegi Gould cood all these things, right? Every belief that any form of Christian
or Jewish person or Muslim would have instant say,
this is a key part of our religion is believing this.
Right?
That is encompassed in that idea of a way of being in the world.
But there's also encompasses, right?
Your peasant farmer who doesn't care about theology.
Right? But who goes and participates in the festivals,
goes and participates in the sacrifices.
Right?
Uh, has
the what anybody would call the quote-unquote religious elements of weddings, funerals,
births, rights of initiation, right? All of these things, right? Yeah. Has that in a non-reflective
or pre-reflective way? Right? Because religion has to include that too. Yeah. Right? So that's
why I use a way of being in the world, not a way of thinking or a worldview, but a way of being in
in the world, right? So the second piece is that it encompasses all
levels of reality. Right. And that sounds I know like a weird
circumlocution. But if we start talking about the natural and
the supernatural or the spiritual and the material, yeah, that's
that's one particular way of looking at that stuff. Right.
You're not going to include all right, all releasing in that.
Yeah, most of what we would consider religion throughout the
history of the world does not think of the world that way does
Does that make those distinct?
right? But the idea is that it encompasses all of reality as reality is conceived by those people.
Right. So that it encompasses everything real. Right. And this is to get away from the idea that
religion is just this element that covers this one part of life. Right. Yes. It's not really how
how religion has functioned.
historically. Right. And most people who think of themselves as religious would not say,
oh, well, that's just this little part of my life over here. I mean, there are
part. Well, like that for sure. There are. But most, yeah, yeah. In the modern era, there are people
like that. Yes. But that is cover most of world history. And then finally, we have the expresses
itself in practices. And that is...
that there is some kind of not just things you do and things you don't do, but that those form a routine or a habit or a cycle or a repeated practices.
And we're using the term practices because this encompasses things like worship,
right? But also encompasses things like ethical considerations.
Yeah. And political considerations in the classical sense. Right. Now politics classically was just
ethics at the level of community. Right. So the way a person should govern their own life
was seen as being of a piece with the way a ruler should govern a city, for example.
Right. Aristotle writes his ethics, then his politics. Right.
So we're using Prank
practices because it encompasses all that.
It encompasses everything from fasting and dietary stuff to how and when you worship and
who leads it and how you structure your family unit and how you write all of these things
are encompassed by this idea of practices.
And practices are kind of inescapable.
Yeah, like, I mean, and this is and this again, not
to pick too much on our Protestant friends, but there is this idea amongst a lot of Protestants,
certainly the kind that I was when I was growing up that had this idea that the practices
you engage in, especially like, for instance, how you worship is kind of optional, right?
Like they would certainly say you should worship, but the particular way in which you do it,
Right, these specific practices of worship, that's kind of a matter of taste or
preference, you know, so it's kind of switch outable, right? And one of the reasons that
on the other side that you can kind of see this is go to the website of almost, frankly,
almost any Protestant church and you will find a statement of faith if they're going to
have, includes something like this, right? A statement of faith and the statement of faith
is a list of beliefs. But rarely is there like a list of practices because the beliefs
are the core thing.
And I remember even hearing
a lot of people will say like one major religious practice obviously is music.
Say, well, it doesn't matter exactly what kind of music you use, as long as the lyrics are expressing the beliefs correctly.
So again, it's this idea that practices are sort of variable and optional and all that kind of stuff.
But again, historically, that's not the case.
And early Protestants, of course, would not have seen it that way either.
Like, this is a more of a modern Protestant kind of idea.
Yeah.
And this is, and we want to be fair.
Part of it is this thing that's been sort of bred
into a lot of our Protestant friends, right?
Like pretty much any Protestant I've ever known,
in a low stakes conversation,
in a low stakes friendly conversation.
If you say, should somebody who becomes a Christian
get baptized, they're going to say yes.
And if you say, if somebody becomes a Christian,
attends Sunday worship, they're going to say yes.
So, you know, somebody who's very precious should-
that they not participated sexual morality,
no, they should not, right, etc, etc, etc.
Right.
But if anyone says that,
even with the word should, a little too forcefully,
right, works righteousness.
Right, there's this blanching,
there's this pulling back of,
well, no, none of those things are required for salvation.
None of those things.
Yeah, there's just a sort of a should but not must.
Right.
But then if you wrap around and say,
well, okay, so wait a minute, wait a minute,
pause, lower the stakes a second, right? Are you saying? Right? That if someone, you know,
comes and says they got saved on this date, but then they never go to church, they never get
baptized and they're a fornicator and a murderer, they're going to go to heaven
because they got saved on that date, and it doesn't matter. And they're going to say, well, no,
They never really got saved then, right?
Yeah, yeah, and if you say well then so aren't you saying those things are required for salvation?
I'm like no, they're not
That's what I mean by the same pivolence, right? Yeah, it's it's I mean, we're not gonna solve this tonight
But it's the whole life works thing we've talked about right in detail before, but that's where that comes just been
Been sort of bred in yeah, and exhibit a they I don't know folks know on on YouTube
The good folks at ancient faith took a clip from our last episode it had
and uh...
of some of the things...
I said to that to the effect of what I just said and the comments section is kind of amazing
Right in the knee jerk reactions
Haza and I say knee jerk reaction because
In some cases it's very clear that there was not any intent to try to figure out what I was actually saying
There was just a reaction like a visceral reaction to this sounds like a
False gospel of works right just
Where right
you
But again, it practices, right?
Every Protestant I know goes to church
at least most Sundays and thinks that does it
because they think they should.
They go and get baptized.
Whenever their church offers communion,
they participate in it.
You know, they refrain from gross sin as best they can
when they do sin, they ask for forgiveness.
Right? Like, I don't know any Protestants who don't do that.
I don't know any Protestants who are like
I'm going to do zero good works between getting saved and dying.
Just to prove to the one who does not work in his record, his grace.
I don't know anyone like that.
I doubt you do either.
If you do, get them help.
So obviously, Protestants are that way.
And acting like Protestants are that way,
like some Roman Catholic apologists do sometimes,
it's just ridiculous and childish.
We get it.
it but you know
We need to be careful with the knee jerk reaction, right?
Because probably even when I said practices, practices, what you got practice it.
Yeah, you do, right?
And we all know you do. We all know you do.
And you can frame it as well. That's part of sanctification, not justification.
Whatever you need to do, so that we can have the conversation. Okay, cool.
But, right?
But there's practices involved, right?
they're just R in religion.
right. This definition is also nice because we don't have to worry about this whole distinction between what is a religion or what is religion and what is philosophy.
Yeah, especially because I mean, this idea of the difference between religion and philosophy, it's like well, people think of the philosophy department,
You know what you guys sitting around thinking thoughts, writing books about those thoughts and teaching.
classes, but I mean ancient philosophy, there were religious, what we would regard as religious
practices. I mean, heck, ancient mathematics. There was, there was religious practice.
They went along with it. Oh yeah. The mysticism of numbers. And, and, and on top of all that,
the church fathers offer referred to Christianity as the true philosophy. Yeah. Yeah. And even,
people who distinguish between philosophy and religion.
knowledge that Pythagoreanism was a religion. Yeah. Yeah.
For example, but Platonist at the academy, they had patterns of fasting.
They spent periods of time in meditation, right? All of all of these things, right?
It was, it wasn't Aristotle's school like in, in a temple of Apollo. Yes.
There you go. Right. So I know you've been told by the Enlightenment. In the Enlightenment,
all of the new the new found atheists
or worshipers of pure reason,
recast, socrates and Plato and Aristotle
is like them in Togas, right?
It's said, oh, just like I have risen above
the superstitious religion of my day,
which is Christianity, they rose above
the primitive religion of their day,
which was Greek paganism.
We've talked about this before,
the show that's absolute nonsense.
Absolutely not sets now.
We're going to talk a little more about that in the second half.
They thought they had a more refined version of religion, right?
But they didn't think it was a separate religion.
They didn't have a concept of a religion.
But they didn't feel like they had absented themselves from the general civic and religious life
of Athens, for example.
They weren't dissent by doing that.
They weren't Quakers living in the midst of Anglicans.
Alright.
And last sort of note, within practices,
another reason why the term practices, I think, is good, is that when we talk about practices,
practices within the same sort of religious milieu can admit a variation based on time and place.
Right? So a good example of that is dietary stuff.
Right, almost all religious expressions have some kind of dieterist.
stuff. It may be stuff you're not allowed to eat ever. It may be fasting patterns, right?
But there's there's something connected to eating. And of course, that's going to be shaped
a little in different parts of the world, right? Different kinds of terrain based on what's
available. Yep, right. And sacrifices are meals. So we're including sacrifices here. What
animals you sacrifice, right? And what kind of grain offerings you offer are going to vary
based on what the local grain
is that are very based on what the local wildlife, what the local domesticated animals are.
And so the fact that there's a difference within that practice based on where you are
does not necessarily mean, oh now this is an entirely different religious expression.
Because there have been deep work and there are no pigs anyway.
accidental the fact that they're living in a
place with no pigs is accidental or the fact that they're now offering rice cakes instead
of wheat cakes is accidental. Right. The fundamental religious expression, the fundamental religious
practice is the same. Yeah. All right. Well, having run through all of that, which is much
more memorable than the philosophy of science, of course, I took back during the late
Neolithic period. We're going to go ahead and take our first break and we'll be right
back with your calls on this episode of The Lurors Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick.
Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
The existence of fools for Christ in the Orthodox tradition mystifies many people.
even some within the Orthodox Church itself.
People often wonder what purpose these sometimes comical and often times tragically misunderstood saints serve in the life of the church, especially given their unconventional and seemingly bizarre behaviors.
In Holy Fools by Oswin Craten, we begin to gain a better understanding of these saints' curious manner of serving Christ,
as we learn about the extraordinary lives of 20 of the most well-known fools for Christ
in a series of bulls-
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
to young. If you have a question call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Hey welcome back everybody. It's the second half
the Lord of Spirits podcast and this is episode 99 if you can believe it. Anybody know exactly
how many hours we've been talking now? I feel like I've been talking to you for a long time.
Yes so next time what said? It's interminable. Interminable. It's probably related to I was thinking
during that commercial, right? Like I've got the whole misunderstood comical fool part down. It's
the same.
part. Oh, that's the tricky bit. I mean, it's easy to throw sausage. It's a
people and say hypocrite hypocrite. Yeah, I mean, yes, who hasn't? Right?
I've been known to throw the sausage or two at some hypocrites. But yeah, so, so,
yeah, this is episode 99 and next episode will be episode 100 and we will also be celebrating
our fourth anniversary. That'll be a nice round numbered episode to just end the show.
with, wouldn't it? Huh? Just a hundred ideas. Good, just sort of, yeah, cash in, take
retirement. I don't know. I'm kind of done talking to you. So I'm not actually employed by
actually faith. So I get no retirement. I'll have to. I'll send you a fruit basket. Not
even a gold watch. Not even a gold watch. Right to the like a fruit basket, fruit
about like an edible arrangement at least.
Ooh, ooh.
I have to see what's available in your area.
Can we get the AFers to spring for that?
You do kind of live in the sticks.
I do not live in the sticks.
I live in a swamp.
Oh, excuse me.
The sticks are all soggy and rotten.
Yeah, like you do live in a soggy place, especially now, after a hurricane.
Yeah, exactly, exactly.
But yeah, so next week, not next week, next time that's two weeks from today is episode
100. It'll be our fourth anniversary. So I hope everybody will, but we'll tune in. It'll be a very,
very special next time on a very special episode of the Lord of Spirits. And I actually will be
not here in the Tower of Podcasting in a Mayas, Pennsylvania, perched high atop the gateway to
the underworld that that is the building that I actually currently in. This is a gateway to
to the underworld to down far beneath me many floors beneath I will be in the very belly of the
the very liver of Leviathan Chester Tinen, Indiana.
Yes. The poor man's so high.
It's true. It's true. I think there's people
sick on YouTube. Like, don't stop.
There's so fathers never.
I mean, at some point, guys, at least one of us is going to die.
It's probably going to be father Steven first.
So I had to put probably your money down.
So although only the good guy young, so.
Um.
I probably shouldn't tell you in advance, but the real reason, the real reason next time
it's going to be a very special episode is that they're luring you to HQ for an intervention.
Oh.
Like Father Andrew, we know you like Father Steven, but no, I think it's one of the token
thing.
Oh, oh, oh.
Yeah.
I mean, it is true.
That is true that I'm ending the Tolkien podcast.
Maybe they're trying to make that go faster or something.
I don't know.
I think it's what you started
commissioning the icons that we all knew that you had a problem.
Yeah, I mean should bowrocks have halos in addition to wings? I don't, I'm not sure yet, but
should it be spelled bar log and should it look like Mike Tyson? These are the real questions.
Wow. Oh man. That's that's a deep cut right there. Nice. So anyway, yeah. So next time
You're in 100. Yeah, thank you. Thank you episode 100
and our fourth anniversary.
It's hard to believe, we've been doing this since 2020.
A lot has happened since then.
We need to get people chanting four more years.
That's what we do.
Come on, do it on YouTube, you guys.
Start chanting four more years in the chats.
They're not doing it.
Yeah.
The young David 24.
Disobedience.
Yeah, okay, where were we?
Well, we're working our way back.
That's true. We spent a lot of that time right in the early modern period. Yeah.
With a couple dips back into ancient Roman ancient Greece. Now we're going to go back even further.
Yeah. All the way back to the year 2000. No. Someone on Facebook is saying four more years.
So Facebook has outstripped the YouTube's this time. Take that YouTube's.
Yeah, there's a very different ecosystem.
in the YouTube live chats. Oh, it's true. Oh, yeah, I say this is someone who has spent hours
mostly trolling in YouTube live chats. There's a whole different vibe. There is. I don't know.
I haven't seen a lot of quality trolling. When I go back and look at the live chat replay,
right? Like, sometimes I can look at the live chat replay. Sometimes I say, now they're saying
form, now they're saying form our years and actually one person's saying 100 more years. Look,
Look, you're not I'm not living a hundred more years. Sorry. You think of them?
vampire like we're going to be lucky to get 20 more years.
Frankly, so the, uh,
yeah, like sometimes I say something during the episode.
And so you guys like take down the live stream and then re upload it as a video,
like to remove what I said.
Um, and so then I can't see the live chat like live chat replay disappears when you do.
Sure. Right.
Sure. But the times when I can, the relatively few times where I can go and look at the live chat replay,
uh, I don't see a lot of quality trolling.
And and I'm not looking at it during the show, but Father Andrew is and Father Andrew is
reminently trollable. Thanks. And so I prove in every episode. It's because I'm I'm just
so tender-hearted. Yes. I mean, anybody compared to you is tender-hearted. Well, that's true.
That's true.
Yeah.
Compared to be weak old stake is tender.
But.
I sometimes experience emotions when you create it.
No feelings.
No feelings just about.
And the emotion is usually rage, but just channel everything into that.
But anyway, we're going back to the middle part of the first millennium BC.
Back in the day.
Yes, even further back in the day.
day.
Even further back than the year 2000.
I like the
it now, you know, when I was a kid, the future was always the year 2000.
I know. I know.
Future. And now we could say like way back in the log ago time,
all the way back in the year 2000. Where are the flying cars?
Yeah. Where? Um, but no, we're not going quite to 2000 BC yet.
We're going to go back further than that. But right now,
we're around 500 BC.
plus or minus 250 years.
Before every book was born. Yeah, so the middle part
Middle part, and congratulations to everybody that's surviving the bell riots since father Andrew brought it up. That's true
So the middle part of the first millennium BC which is referred to as the Axial Age
AXIAL
Yeah, not the Axial Age
Which would be either a Beverly Hills cop reference or something like guns and roses exactly
Yeah. But this is the axial age. That term came from a was coined by a 20th century German,
early 20th century German. And I know what you're thinking. What you're thinking? Slow down.
He was German Swiss.
He was the more peaceful, neutral kind of German.
Right?
Early...
20th century Germans.
Lot of lots of great stuff, but Swiss.
He's Swiss, okay.
Supplier he was bodyguards to the Pope.
Right.
He was probably just, you know, depositing
the wealth of those evil Germans from Germany proper.
In Swiss banks.
I just slide during this anthropologist for no reason.
Like anyway, his name is Jasper's by the way.
It's a good German name.
That's the coolest.
happening. Anyway, so he coins this term to describe this period for the center portion
of the the first of the LED and BC, and the reason he wants to coin a term to describe
this age or this era is that there is this massive transition, massive shifting of religious
forms literally all over the world at that time.
And by all over the world, I mean from China to Greece to Egypt to Judea to right anywhere
you want to pick.
What are some of the things that are going on during this period?
Well, if we're talking about Judaism, we get really the existence of Judaism proper,
right?
this period, the...
The Hebrew Scriptures are being compiled, edited, right?
In some cases, for some books composed, right?
Yeah, this is post-exile.
Like, when they come back from Babel, well, the RFP is the exile.
Right, that's the beginning of Second Table Judaism.
Yeah, I mean, there are, there are, of course, some people who claim,
and, you know, I would just say to people,
people listen to some of the recent
Hall Council of God episodes.
Some people who claim that the whole Hebrew scriptures were written written at this period,
but there's all kinds of internal evidence that says that that is not the case.
But that's why I talked about in some cases composition,
the other cases compilation and editing.
Yeah, because I mean the Hebrew scriptures were written over a long period.
Yeah.
But you also have in addition to that, this transformation in what becomes Judaism
over against right the religion,
and innovation, Israel, and Judah.
Judaism, you see the rise of synagogues. You see the rise of the Pharisees as a class of
scribes and textual scholars because you have, right, the scriptures being composed, edited,
compiled, right. And the forms, right, the forms that pre-existed that, the forms from
ancient Israel and ancient Judah still exist. There's a second temple there, the temples
functioning, sacrifices are being offered, the same fees are being, all those things are
still happening from the Torah that we're happening before the exile.
In terms of religious phenomena, but you also now have this shift in these new religious
phenomena related to the text of the Hebrew Scriptures and related to the scholars of that
text and the Synagogue system as a means of gathering and religious observance.
right? So that's a change, that's a shift. Yeah. There's continuity, but there's also now this
this new layer, this new phenomenon that gets added. If you want to go over to Greece,
right at the very beginning of this period, you have Homer and Hessean writing,
and then once you get to the middle of this period, you've got the rise of philosophy and philosophical
schools in Greece.
You might think like Homer and Hezier, how is that a big change?
Well, most indications are that a lot of what they're writing
was existed in some kind of oral form.
Right.
And now it's being written down.
That kind of fixes it in a way that shifts.
It's not quite the same.
Probably the same content.
but now you're getting stuff
written down. It's a literary function now.
And the reading and interpretation of, for example, Homer's text is going to become the basis
of education for a couple thousand years.
Yeah, which that would not have been the period.
Yeah, right. I mean, that would be very different if it remained purely an oral thing.
Right.
Very, very different.
Right. If you want to go over to China, right, Lao Tzu is in this period, the Daoji
the founders of
Almost every school of what's considered quote unquote Chinese philosophy, right, are all during this period
If you want to go to India, bootism emerges in this period
If you want to go to Persia, Zoroastrianism emerges in this period
so
there is
something happening
right all over the world during this period and
And that's why
there was a need for anthropologists studying this period and studying real
ancient religion to say we need to term for this era this this period of time
when the shifts are happening worldwide right and when we look at those shifts
you may have already noticed as we were giving examples there are some
through lines right there there are some there are some similar particular
phenomena that are going on.
in these different places.
And so we could talk about some,
especially within paganism, right?
So Old Testament religion, right?
Ancient Israel's religion and Judaism
is a little bit of a special case,
but we'll come back to that.
Because there are some through lines there too.
But everywhere else we're talking about forms of paganism,
right?
And so there's some things we can see.
So one of them is...
the de-personalization or the relativization of spirits and gods, right, within paganism.
So for example, Plato's forms, we've talked about this on the show before, Plato's forms
are basically the Greek gods and goddesses stripped of all of the anthropomorphic personhood.
Yeah.
Right.
Which, played, I'll read the youth of-
right, believes is unworthy to ascribe to them. Right. So instead of a God of justice who
is a flanderer and goes around doing these things, right, you have justice itself.
Yeah. And you know, you even get stuff that's kind of in between like,
you know, early, you get this idea of muses, these very specific goddesses who inspire people to do
particular artistic things.
But then you also have this sense of like,
like we might describe the spirit of music.
But when someone says that,
they don't mean a spirit exactly.
But there's this, yeah, it's a deep, as you said,
it's a deep personalization,
but still with a sense of a spiritual reality.
And the personal elements get relativized, right?
Yeah.
So you still have Plato and Aristotle
engaging in meditative practice.
Right, to connect with things that they think are divine.
They've just sort of depersonified them.
Right, made them less human in the sense
of possessing human foibles.
But you can also see this, similarly frankly,
in the move of Buddhism out of Hinduism,
the way, again, most forms of Buddhism.
treat the idea of gods and spirits from within Hinduism, right?
Where it's not sort of like, well, we deny all those things exist anymore than Plato did, but they become relativized, right?
They become principles, they become kind of depersonified, they become tools or elements of a ladder that might be useful to someone
spiritually at a certain level of their development, but there are sort of more refined forms.
that go beyond that. Right? So this is not in either case, right, a rejection of the preceding
pagan religion, but it is a participation from the perspective of those first participants
of leaders. There's a participation in any more refined or purified or more noble or
or worthy form of that religion.
Sometimes it kind of that religious expression, reinterpretation or additional layer of interpretation.
Yeah.
You also find a shift away from...
So what you find in, for example, a lot of ancient near Eastern religion and paganism
is the idea that
You know, the world is full of spirits and gods and
Overplaces over things and do things and they're they're fundamentally capricious
Yeah, they're just dangerous beings that exist in your area and you want to keep them from hurting you right and kind of fickle
They'll turn on you. They're easily offended right
Sometimes you just don't want them to know about you at all right
You can see this in Greek paganism too.
I mean, this is kind of a through line in paganism.
right? And so ritual and sacrifice and these things are often aimed at almost
bribing or winning over, right? Gaining the allegiance of these spirits and
spiritual forces and and and gods, right? And you see in these more refined forms
that emerge in the Axial Age, a shift from that to an understanding that there
is some kind of order or structure.
or harmony or path within the world itself.
Yeah, there's even, I mean, almost you could say
there's a sense that there is the world, you know?
Yeah.
That there's something more than just this.
Right.
Yeah.
And so that what that means then is that
if there is this kind of order structure harmony
within the world, you can start having the concept
like FX.
Right. Ethics and religion are so closely tied together in our minds, right, as modern
people because we've come from a Christian society that we don't understand that there
was not any real fundamental connection or even really a sense of ethics. Yeah, this
idea, right? We've written wrong. I mean, really, it's much more like good and bad in
the sense of like.
This is a good chair and that is a bad job.
Well, I'm talking even before that.
Oh yeah. Right.
Even before that.
I'm talking about before the that starts to emerge in the axial age.
Like before that in large part, it's right.
The the you know, the king goes and you know, post in a prominent place like the coat of homerabi.
Right. Here's the laws.
And here's what I will do to you if you break them.
Right.
But if you're not in that city, there's not a law.
You just out there.
Right.
I'm going to make you.
And the same thing with the gods, right.
There are certain things that you wouldn't do because you thought, you know, right?
Like read some Greek tragedy, right?
You do certain things and the furies are going to come up out of 80s and get you.
Right, but it was fear of getting got. Right. It wasn't how do I need to behave and live in order to
live a fulfilling and successful life? Right. As part of a community that is thriving. Right. There
was no concept of that. Right. There was no concept of that. Right. You are either in survival mode
or you were enslaved or you were the one doing the enslaved
living. Right, but there was not this sense of like there's a way I need to live in the
world. You know, and that our community needs to be governed so that it will thrive and
grow and be successful. Right. And that included, right, when you get that idea coming about
in the axioli to these various places, that included the divine. That wasn't to the exclusion
of the gods. It wasn't like, oh, don't worry about the gods anymore. The gods were
included in that, right? Like you're you needed to be in harmony with your family, your
community with you with the gods, right? With the divine, right? All of those things, that's
how you wanted to live your life so that all would go well with you. And even then still
sometimes bad things happen by chance. Yeah, right. But there's still this idea, right,
that there was a should, so that people should live.
And, you know, be careful, right?
Because even as I'm saying that,
I'm trying to choose by where carefully,
because we as modern people want to individualize that.
Yeah, it's much more like,
what's good for the community as a whole?
Right, how can the community flourish?
So at this point in the actual age,
things are very communal and the should
is very dependent on your social class, for example.
Yeah.
So have you?
a slave than what you should do is work really hard at whatever you're ordered to do.
It's understandable that the communal is so privileged because
hanging together it meant the difference between survival and you know,
extension. So the yeah, the kind of ethics we're talking about right now though is not,
you know, live your best life now, right? No.
like, sorry, they fully embraced it.
They fully embraced it.
way that we as modern people will not admit, they fully embraced on the face of it, that
for some people to prosper and have a very high standard of living, a whole lot more would
have to not.
Right.
Like, they just took that program and they were at no problem with the idea.
Yes.
And everybody was in the social strad that they were because that's where they belonged.
And even, you know, they were even...
detailed arguments that certain kinds of people were just sort of born to be slaves or born to be
masters, you know, whatever. Or born to be merchants or born to be great generals or born to be
soldiers, right? Like at all the different levels, right? And so there's a different
ought. There's a different ethic for each of them. And the aim of it is not really yet, right? I mean
they accepted when they went to war that a lot of those infantry guys were going to die.
Yeah, right.
And
them going out there and dying bravely, wasn't so great for them, right? Or their individual families,
but it was great for Athens, and that's what was important. Right. Yeah. So don't individualize
this too quickly, but it is still a watershed having this idea of ethics, right? And having the idea of
having a, that there's this harmony and order in the world that is reflected in that. And it's not
just the Caprice of God.
and kings and larger people right with more physical strength, right, that govern the world.
Right, and so we can see elements of this though. We can see some elements of this though,
even in this transition from the religion of ancient Israel and Judah to Judaism, right,
especially Phariseism.
Phariseism has a very strong sense of...
ethics, right? The Torah when it was given, because I believe it was given well, well, well pre-exile,
the Torah when it was given was talking about how to structure the society, how Israel should be
structured, right? And what Israel should and should not allow within its limits, right? Because we
We have to understand that no one in Israel virtually could read...
the pre-exilic period. The king was to, according to Deuteronomy, have a copy of the Torah and read it,
because he needed to know what to allow and what not to allow and how to structure and maintain order in
the people of Israel, how to administer the temple and its rituals, etc. etc. etc.
Right, the priest needed to know the
those things, right, in Leviticus, right?
These people needed to know it.
But your average ancient Israelite, or ancient Judahite,
had pretty much no knowledge of what was in the Torah,
contents of the Torah.
There were not like Torah readings.
There was no Gideons at the Tabernacle.
And if they had done a Torah reading of the Tabernacle,
only the priests would have heard it anyway, right?
Because the people didn't all go to the Tabernacle
on Saturday to worship.
Yeah, nobody as we've talked about it the show that's not how it worked. Yeah, we're the temple later, right? That didn't happen
Um, and in the north they're thinking of course it's even worse because they're engaging in all kinds of pagan worship and stuff right there
Not a tourist role to be found right for a normal person
um
Whereas
Right post exile once you have the synagogue system you do start having public Torah readings
Ezra does read the Torah publicly.
Start having a lot of writing and literary activity.
So now your average Jewish person who's going to a synagogue is hearing the Torah.
And so those commandments take on a new pertinence to them.
So the Pharisees still believed
that the solution to the problem, the ongoing problem of exile and Roman oppression
that Israel, right at that time Judea, had to corporately keep the Torah. But the way
someone participated in corporately keeping Torah was by keeping Torah themselves.
Which Torah they now heard read at a synagogue. And so the Torah took on in this period
an ethical dimension.
For Jewish people that it did not originally have a new dimension for them.
So these shifts, even though we're talking about different original religious structures,
shift does still take place. A parallel shift does still take place.
to produce what becomes early Judaism, ancient Judaism, second-tabled Judaism,
right, in all of its diverse forms. So what causes this? Right? Why does this happen all over the world
at this, during this era in history? Right? Well, there's a number of factors that play into it.
Right, so first and foremost,
You have sort of the stabilization,
a stabilization of society during this period.
So remember, we're coming off the Bronze Age collapse
at the end of the Second Millennium BC.
It kind of throws everything into chaos.
And I've said, I know I've said before on this show
and I've said to lots of people,
when you're envisioning the time period of David and Saul
and even into Solomon.
Right at the beginning of the first millennium BC,
you've got to picture it in a sort of post-apocalyptic.
The people are living in and around the ruins of the great Bronze Age civilizations.
And there are people trying to take up those mantles, like the Assyrians will be trying to
sort of when they show up, after a few centuries, will be trying to sort of take on the mantle
a
Babylon. Right. And then they're followed by the neo-Babalonian empire, right, who are
most certainly trying to lay claim to the empire of homerabe, right, to which they're not
related, right? And trying to rebuild that, right? And and reproduce that. The Philistines
here running into our refugees.
From the Aegean who have come and settled in the...
of want. Are these the C peoples? Yes. Yes, part of the city. One of the C peoples. Right.
So there are a bunch of Greeks who washed up on shore who are trying to structure some
kind of society now in their new environments because they tried to take over Egypt and
got repelled. Right. Along with other C peoples groups. Right. In the area. Right. So this
is this is this kind of post apocalyptic and rebuilding period. So once we get into the middle
part.
of the first millennium BC, things have been rebuilt.
We've now got the Greek city states functioning in Greece in the classical period, after the
collapse of the Mycenaeans.
Egypt has kind of recovered economically and financially.
The Assyrians are on the rise trying to rebuild Babylon.
The things have stabilized, right?
Things have been rebuilt to a certain...
level. Right. And then you're going to get the Neobabillonians. Then you're going to get the Persians.
Right. And the Persians during this period are forming their religions or ashrinism. All of this
is being built. Right. And taking shape, their whole culture and sense of self is taking place
during this axiallage. Right. All of this is happening. Similar things are happening in India and China
in terms of rebuilding and so things
reach a certain level of stability.
Because all of the other factors we're about to talk about
that contributed to the axial age require you to have
some kind of stability, right?
Economically in terms of the class structure of your society,
right, if you're being invaded, if you're being attacked,
if you're at war, if you're suffering from famine and plague,
you're not going to have time to learn to read.
Yeah, or there's not a lot of people who can be sitting.
around writing big long literature, you know, it's like, look, pick up a spear buddy. Yeah.
So that's why a lot of this starts happening, right, in this period. We first we get this
stability. And then as we've kind of already alluded to, you get an economic situation where you
have the emergence of a very strong class system within these agrarian economies, right, mostly based
on slavery.
in various forms.
But as we mentioned, they're very conscious about the fact that, yes,
for these upper tiers of society to enjoy a certain lifestyle,
and certain things, to have leisure time, to be able to have time to devote to these other things,
there has to be this great pool of people who are meeting their survival needs
In terms of food, shelter, etc., etc., etc., tribute tax.
All of this has to happen.
And those structures come into place.
Those structures come into place so that you can have a class of people, a literate class.
And so the development of this literate class means there's this rise of literacy rates.
This is also the period of time where people are now
At this time using alphabetic language for the most part
Yeah, as as as distinct from some of the kind of you know pictogram approaches pictographic or
Consonato vocabulary is kuneiform
This is important because this is a prerequisite for having a very high literacy rate
Right is is that you limit the number of characters that you have to learn
Right when you're looking at different forms of kuneiform like simplified kuneiform alphabets have like
80 symbols, the simplified ones.
Right?
You're not going to have a ton of literate people,
right? And that sort of situation.
Whereas, an alphabetic language
where each symbol represents a sound,
and there's, you know,
20, 22, 24, 26 of them, right?
Much more workable.
Right? Much more workable in terms of literacy.
Let's see.
get this rise of a literate class. That means people start taking oral tradition, stories,
writing all these things that have been handed down orally and putting in them into writing
and all they're putting in writing, but there are people who are able to read them and
they begin to be read publicly. And so you get the rise of public discourse.
Yeah, and then, and then, you know, because of that, then you get rituals that are connected
with this use of texts. Right. So you start having right the Torah of
read in the synagogues, right? Or you start having Homer being sung and performed publicly,
right? And similarly in other cultures, right? It's not just a storyteller telling their
version of the story that's localized and related to particular traditions, but they start to take
on this larger form, right? And so you get a sort of enlarged religious significance of the tag.
So this shift, the reason we've been talking about this shift, there's someone out there
who's like, wait a second, I thought this episode was going to be about the Stone Age.
And I warned you at the beginning, we would not get there to the third half.
They say, why are you, why are you dilly dallying in the middle of the first millennium BC?
Well, so this, that we've been talking about the exilage, there's this apoccal shift
we've been describing in religion.
across the world. And this one's really well documented, because we've got all these texts from it.
Right? So we could describe it, we could research it, you can look at it, you can look at it in
various countries spread out all over the world, you can compare and compare it. Right? It's all documented.
This is not the first major shift like this, though. There was a previous shift in the Neolithic era
in the Stone Age. Right?
That one is not documented because there was no writing.
It's prehistoric.
Right?
And so we've spent this time here in the second half talking about the axial age and
this shift to give an idea of how this kind of thing works.
Right?
Since this one is so well documented, to help us understand now, as we in the third half,
go back even way further.
We're going to go further back from the axial aids than the axial aids.
is from us to talk about what happened in the Neolithic revolution and what's going on there
religiously.
Yeah.
All right.
We're going to go further back in time in the next half of Lord of Spirits.
But now we're going to go ahead and take our second and final break.
See you in a moment.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of spirits. Give them a call.
call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
People often complain that the divine
liturgy is always the same, weak after weak.
But every ritual, phrase, and action in the service
has meaning and purpose. Drawing in worshipers
with its hymns and prayers and allowing
ordinary people to lead.
the world and enter heaven for a short time. In the new book, Blessed is the Kingdom, Father
Stavros, Akrotarian Aakis, a long-time parish priest, offers reflections on the text of the Divine
Liturgy of Saint John Chrysostom to help readers learn, to pray the liturgy, and to understand
and appreciate the mystery that unfolds each time it is celebrated. Available now at store.enginefaith.com.
Again, the restore.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back everybody.
It's the third and final half of this 99th episode of the Laura Spirits podcast next time.
It's gonna be a personal
100 and our fourth anniversary. So what happened to that ad for your new show?
It was too long apparently. Well, I know it was a lot. Oh, really? Like no,
so I was gonna say I kind of liked it. I could go get a cup of coffee. So that's true. It was a
little yeah. Come back in time for the next half. Look, we got a cell books. Okay, I mean
and did your co-host, Rip Rogers, get in trouble?
No, no, no, he's still, he's still.
on board. You know, you know, the weird thing about him is it is now that I met him in person.
Like, you know, on, on, when you hear him on ancient faith and a podcast or something,
he kind of sounds like he's affecting a little bit of a light English accent.
You know, I think so. A little bit, a little bit, you know, but that level of
affectation, that's commonplace for a southerner, right? Like, yeah, we deal with that. But here's
What's weird when you meet him in person?
He constantly speaks in this fake Jama-
in Patois. And I don't know like who he thinks he's fooling, like that that's his natural
voice. Like I went to Peshau fast, he's sticking his head out of the sunroof for the car
yelling original rude boy while we're driving around Tampa. I don't know what's with this
guy. I mean, I mean, look, the guy's name is Richard Roland. He is literally a living
Rick Rawl.
If that is his real name.
So yes, yes, I mean, it might be his legal name.
I'm just saying.
I understand.
You have to nod.
It's just odd.
I'm not going to say it's racist, but it's weird.
Where were we?
The Stone Age Paleolithic, Mesolithic, Neolithic, exolithic,
Yeah, hyperlithic.
Yeah, although I also I also want to point out some people may be wondering as soon as you hear Stone Age
If you're of a certain age you may think of the modern Stone Age family the Flintstones
Right, we celebrate Christmas
Yeah, well, it hears why you know why right?
I've never really considered that question actually there's this misnomer that the Flintstones are living in ancient times
Right
like this
to some kind of, you know,
Ken Ham, does the honeymooners,
where you've got, you know,
humans and dinosaurs living side by side.
I mean, it is true that their theme song says
that they are a modern stony.
Moderns, I am like.
Right.
The Flintstones is a post-apocalyptic show
set in the far future.
They're trying to recreate modern technology
with primitive tools.
I'm on board with this.
And that's why they celebrate Christmas.
So Flintstones is actually farther in the future.
then the Jetsons.
Then the Jetsons.
Yes.
We can just go home now, everybody.
But we're now back in the past.
We're now back in the past.
So I mentioned the,
the period of our first,
our first New Zealander tuning in.
Hello New Zealander.
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
Wow.
No, no, no, no calls.
He's just so stunned at this revelation about the Flintstones are like yeah, I don't even know what to do with myself. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah
They may not even I mean
He got visited by an alien
The great gazoo. Oh
Yeah, and there's free masons and the schmoo like come on. Okay, so
Yes, so we mentioned the neolithic revolution
right. And this was not a
class struggle in the Neolithic era. The Neolithic revolution is not a political revolution.
It was not televised but not even written about because as I mentioned at the end of the
second half, it was prehistoric. That's what prehistoric means.
Literally, right.
Yes.
Yeah. So there's no writing about anything. So we know about it from the remains of human
settlements.
and other archaeological remains and certain biological and genetic considerations,
not with humans but with plants and animals, we'll get into that in a minute.
So the Neolithic Revolution happens across the fertile crescent, which is that sort of green
arch on that map that they showed you in seventh grade social studies.
that goes sort of over the top of the Middle East.
It happened throughout that area between about 10,000 and 8,000 BC,
in different places at different times.
I will give my usual disclaimer, if you don't think the Earth is that old,
just accordingly, I find the whole question tedious and boring.
So, commonly dated to between 10,000 and 8,000 BC,
see.
And that's right after the end of the last ice age, right?
And again, feel free to think whatever you want
about the relationship between that ice age and the flood,
that the evidence of that ice age
is actually evidence of the flood,
that the flood is describing the massive earth changes
that happened at the end of that ice age.
However you wanna see it, you do you.
Okay.
But that's the most zoomer thing I've ever heard you say.
You do you.
Yeah.
No cap.
Anyway.
Um, you've got such a Riz father, Steven.
Did you hear?
Did you hear that sound father Andrew?
Sound of billions of souls cringing and then falling silent.
Um, so, uh, during this period, the important thing.
The important thing, and what the Neolithic Revolution is describing, the revolutionary thing that happens
is that this is the period of time when humans begin to domesticate plants and animals.
People don't think about domesticating plants much.
But if you go to...
And there are fossilized examples of this.
Right.
look at what wild wheat looked like before humans domesticated wheat. It's a very different
thing. Oh yeah. Much more difficult to process into something edible. Right. So yes, all
of the all of these plants that became agrarian staples for humans in human agrarian settlements
existed before human agrarian settlements, right? But they existed as wild plants.
And wild plants are often difficult to process into edible form.
If not difficult, they're often inefficient to process an edible form.
And so humans throughout history and prehistory, because all human beings throughout the history
the world has been just as smart as us.
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
I know.
How can that possibly be true?
Have been just as smart as us.
They figured out without any knowledge of genetics,
how to do selective breeding of plants and animals.
Mind blowing.
Yes.
They figured out how to do this.
And it took a long time, right?
The struggle of civilization.
We should respect it.
This is why I don't go camping.
My ancestors fought for centuries,
so I wouldn't have to live that way.
But this domestication of plants and animals is what's required for there to be a continuous
human settlement.
So before this, people are living in groups, extended family groups mostly, living by
hunting and gathering, meaning people migrated nomatically following a
Animals that we're gonna be used for food because animals migrate right so as the animals migrated the people migrated to hunt the animals and
Then they gathered wild
From wild plants other food stuffs right hooken
Huh cooken it's my great
Okay
So they they're following them right if you're going to if you're going to put down roots if you say we're gonna build
build a village here. We're going to build our tents here. We're going to build more
permanent structures here. We're going to stay here in this spot. Then you're going to
need a way to generate food and feed the group of people who are going to be living in that
spot. And since animals migrate away, that's going to be hard. Weather conditions change
from season to season, that's going to be hard.
Right.
You're going to eventually...
exhaust the supply of wild berries and plant life, right? That's edible, right? So all that's going to be difficult. So the only solution to that problem is
we need to start
domesticating plants and growing the food we need deliberately in a way that we can grow it season after season year after year.
And we're going to need to domesticate some of these animals. Now by domesticating animals in this period of history, I'm not talking about like
domesticating horses to ride.
them. Right. Yeah. This is about food. That's thousands of years after that. Right. This is,
we're going to selectively breed sheep and goats. Right. So that they're a little less
honry. Right. And we can get them into a pasture. Right. We can get them into an enclosure.
Right. We can shepherd them. We can take them around and let them graze. Right. And raise
them for food, right, etc. That kind of...
of domestication, whether it's sheep, pigs, goats, right, livestock. That's what we're
talking about domesticating at this point in the history as a food source. So rather than
going and finding them, we're going to bring them here, keep them pinned up, breed them,
and eat them rather than hunting them. So that's what's required. Right? So we also need
to keep in mind that the world population
At this point is very low.
People debate like everything else how low, right?
But everyone agrees.
Again, regardless of what you think the relationship between the evidence for the ice age and the
flood is, right?
You're completely secular, right?
Anthropologist will tell-
you is that depending on their estimate during the ice age at one point, right, during this
period when the ice age evidence exists, the human population of the world they will say
fell to somewhere between 10,600. 600 is the low estimate, 10,000 is the high estimate.
That's not the human population of an area, that's the human population of the earth.
Yeah
Right I mean
My town is 11,500 people.
Right.
So that's not quite giving you seven, right, if you're very literal, right, about Noah's
flood and only the seven people on the arc surviving it.
But it's an acknowledgement that something happens, right?
It's a period that greatly diminishes the human population to with this type.
A lot fewer people.
this tiny amount right of the whole earth.
Right. By the time we get to the period of the Neolithic Revolution that we're talking about,
right, you still have this wide variation. The sort of the low estimate is 55,000 people.
The high estimates are between 1 and 5 million. But if we take 5 million as the highest, again,
that's 5 million in the whole earth.
Right, five million people is probably, I bet there's five million people in the state of New York.
I mean, there's five million people, there's more than five million people in the city of New York.
In the city of New York, okay.
So eight point, yeah, exactly.
Okay.
Yeah.
I'm a West Coast guy.
Eight point three million.
Currently spread out a little more.
We don't pile up.
So yeah.
So this is, if you think that on the high estimate, the entire population of the earth was
lower.
still at this point, then the population of the city of New York.
Right? This is a very different time. By the time you get to, by the way, by the time
you get to 1000 BC. So the time we were talking about, after the Bronze Age collapse and everything,
the time of King's David in Saul, right, in terms of Bill of a Chronology. 1000 BC,
were about 40...
14 million people in the whole world, which I think is roughly the population of say Greece
today
You just throwing this stuff out and making me look it up. I
Increases about 10 million people. It's about 10 and a half million 10 and a half. Okay, so it's a little bigger than Greece. Maybe Germany
and
Now Germany is 84 million
Oh, well, for Pete say, yeah, we're not going to keep guessing. Okay, we're not going to
get power by comparison. Okay, a small European country. The population of a small European
country that will remain nameless. Five Lithuanias. Yes, there we go. That's the whole population
of the earth in 1000. Yeah, right. I don't think we realize, right, how small I got. But
But especially this point we're talking about the Neolithic Revolution.
Right, we're talking about again, even on the highest estimate,
way fewer people than live in the city of New York in the world.
Yeah, right, on Earth.
So these are these settlements, right, these are not even like Sumerian city states.
Right, I know they made that, they made that movie 10,000 BC, which I enjoy for its ridiculousness,
where they have like the mammoths, they're using the mammoths to build pier-
pyramids. Oh yeah. Zigarats and stuff. That's crazy. But anyway, it's crazy. So get that
out of your head. There are no, right? We're talking about settlements. Right. We're talking
about one of these extended family units that had been wandering from place to place, following
game putting down roots and establishing a place. And when this happens,
Right, when this happens, there is a corresponding shift in religion that is detectable in the archaeological record.
Okay, there is a shift that happens.
And we've talked about some of this in previous episodes, a little bit at least, from another angle.
By the way, I just want to interrupt you, Father, because we actually do have some people who are calling.
Oh, I'm good. So since we're here in the third
half we might as well go ahead and take some of them. So yeah, we've got we've got someone who
wants to fact check something you said earlier, father. So about the footsteps. Yeah, we have
Caleb who's you know, he pulled out his copy of Deuteronomy. He's like now hold on a minute,
hold on a minute. So Caleb, are you there? Yes, I am here. Greetings, father's reading a father's
Stephen and Father Andrew.
Welcome.
So I didn't mess up your names.
Yeah, yeah.
So, yeah, you're ready to fact check Father Steven DeYoung?
Well, I hate to put it that way.
I never would.
At any rate, oh, I would.
Well, clearly you're a liberal because fact checking is liberal.
Oh, my God.
Go ahead.
So as first a whole population question, that was hilarious.
I will say, it's getting harder to be someone, but it all works out.
I was thinking we should also remind us we've others to see when we had one of your
chancers visit at our parish up here in the U.P. of Michigan a little while ago and really
appreciated him.
Well, it's good someone appreciates him.
All right.
My question is Deuteronomy 31.
There's a command that their Moses commands that the Torah should be read in the hearing
of all the people once every seven years.
I didn't hear your whole spiel earlier. I'm actually on break at work, but I was wondering how that fits into
Yeah, I mean obviously it wasn't followed most of the time but yeah
It was followed
Yeah, it pretty much wasn't followed at least during the
It looks like it wasn't followed much at all. I would assume Joshua did it and we have record of Joshua doing it once
in the book of Joshua. In the book of Joshua, he does it at one point. But in the period of the judges, it wasn't done.
And we know because we know when when King Josiah, like rediscovered it in the temple.
Yeah, it's all new to him even.
Right.
And.
Oh, this stuff.
Yeah.
Okay.
So.
It was basically like the first generation after Moses
and then it just disappeared until say the time.
Right, it fell into disuse, right?
And you see the same thing happening.
I mean, in general, right?
The story of the book of judges
is about the people sort of forgetting everything
and where the tabernacle falls into disuse.
They start creating other shrines and altars and things.
There's just sort of this immediate falling way
And then there's sort of a, and, and,
And judges, of course, ascribes that too, well Israel needs a king, right?
Sort of set this straight and then sort of helps position moving through the deuteronomistic
history into versus second Samuel or versus second kingdoms that David is the guy, right?
But then things fall apart pretty quickly again after David.
Okay.
even his we also know from the Josiah story that Solomon puts
say an idol of the sun gods chariot in the temple courts. Yeah, yeah, yeah, assume that
this was possibly obeyed during the reign of David, a reign of David and Solomon, perhaps.
Solomon would probably be pushing it maybe, maybe David. Okay, but for the most part,
it wasn't it wasn't being.
It wasn't being followed.
All right.
And they also, we know from Jeremiah,
never kept the Sabbath year either,
which if it was done every seventh year,
that's when it would have been done.
Oh, yeah, huh.
That makes sense.
It's kind of into that.
Yeah.
Yeah, so that'd be a good way of actually seeing.
Or how would you say extrapolating whether it was actually being done or not?
Yeah, yeah, because
God tells Jeremiah, you basically, you're going to be an exile for 70 years because you
owe me 70 Sabbath years that you didn't keep over the last 490 years.
Right.
Yeah.
So I'll preach that one to American agriculture.
Good luck.
Thank you for the father's side.
I need to get back into work.
All right.
Have a good call.
Thanks for calling Caleb.
All right.
We have another caller.
actually. So since we're pause, we're going to go ahead and take Catherine. So Catherine,
welcome to Lord of Spirits podcast. Hi, fathers. How are you? Good. How are you?
I'm excellent. I do have, it's maybe an adjacent question, but it's a, it's a serious question,
and I was wondering in the description of this, of this podcast, I, I saw the word neolithic.
Yep.
And that just fired off a couple things in my mind.
And I was wondering if you could answer them.
Since neolithic, the epitomology of it,
if I'm not mistaken, means new stone.
Right?
There's like three parts of the stone age, paleolithic,
mesolithic, and neolithic.
And that's the latest part is the neolithic period.
Okay.
Okay, because what I was thinking is if there's a new,
there has to be an old.
And so I'm wondering if-
That's the paleolithic.
Okay, so in regards to that,
is that pre-flood or pre-bable
or where people writing things down?
I'm just wondering, where does that start?
Like what is the difference?
did they have the-
neolithic period after the flood or after Bable, or before in regards, you know, just to writing in general.
What do you think, Father? I mean, there's so many different ways you could shake this question out, I guess.
Well, yeah. So it partially depends on what you think is the relationship, as I mentioned, very briefly between the ice age, the last ice age and the flood.
So there are some...
people who would say that all of the archaeological and geological evidence of the last ice age
is really evidence of the flood. So they would say that basically that the last ice age is the flood.
Right, they would identify those two things. There are other folks who would say that
that the story that the story of the flood is telling.
Right? That's sort of when that happens is at the end of the last ice age. So at the
end of the last ice age, according to archaeology and geology, there were these massive earth
changes, meaning the ice age is called the ice age because glaciers expanded over, like,
for example, most of North America was covered by ice or water, water in some form. Right?
there is evidence for it.
So the people who say...
Well, that is the flood would say, well, that was liquid water.
It was the flood, right?
But other people would say, well, no, that was glacier.
But then at the end of that ice age, those glaciers melted.
And when those glaciers melted, they released the trapped water.
So for example, there's archaeological evidence of a couple of cities at the bottom of the black sea.
Hmm, so there's pretty good evidence now that...
that during the the ice age there was no water in the black sea.
And that there were people living there. And at the end of the ice age,
right, as the glaciers melted, it filled up with water and became the black sea.
Right. So some people would say, well, no, the flood happens at the end of the last ice age
when the glaciers melt, right, and it wipes out all of these all of
human civilization as it had stood, right, using the Black Sea as an example.
There are plenty of other examples beside the Black Sea, right?
May I make a point? Sure. I've worked in Northern Alberta and a lot of the in Canada
and a lot of the geological formation is water that was above forests.
So, if it froze, it...
It was forced there and then it was water.
Yeah.
So for me, I don't see it as flood post-ISH.
Right. Well, in my regard.
Yeah, however you want to look at.
But so the idea is the neolithic period is the period right after the ISH.
So if you connect the ISH to the flood, it would be the period after the flood.
And so we would be talking about the when we talk about the Neolithic Revolution, we would be talking about if that's your understanding, we would be talking about the period of time where the population grows to the level that we've been talking about.
And so it starts to build cities and towns and right, well, villages at this point starts to build villages and settle down in permanent places and begins, begins more intentional agriculture.
culture.
Okay, so it's after the flood, but before Bable?
I would say yes, because I think the Tower of Bable is actually related to the Bronze
Age collapse.
Yeah.
Okay.
Thank you.
All right.
Thanks for calling, Catherine.
Okay.
So, yes, world population.
Very small.
So, yeah, so there's this transition in religion that happens as there's this transition to
settled life, right?
And to kind of understand that we have to start with a little bit of an idea of what does hunter-gatherer religion look like?
and look like.
Right. And we've talked about this. We've read a couple of quotes. You can go back to old episodes, very early episodes.
And here's some of the quotes about early quote-unquote monotheism. We've already reiterated this episode why quote-unquote monotheism may not be the most helpful category to have in our head.
But just the idea that early on in the hunter gatherer period of
There is pretty good evidence, right, that we're dealing with primarily one sort of deity
or spirit that people understand to be associated in some way with the sky, with the heavens,
right, above them.
Yeah.
I mean, a lot of the early, you know, even even the lot of the early Indo-European stuff
is the the the mean.
God is, as you said, in some way, kind of like a sky God or a heavenly God or something like that.
Right. Right. And there's sort of one. And then what happens once we start moving to settled life,
is that the earth suddenly becomes very important because now we're going to live by planting and
growing crops. Yeah. The idea of, yeah, I'm kind of deity in the earth or related to the earth. You want
that spirits.
attention and help. Right. The ground, the soil, the fertility of the soil,
right, becomes eminently important. And so you start also getting, and the Neolithic period is
when we get these first cultic figures of an earth goddess. Right. And so there comes to be this
pairing in this early phase, right. And coming out of the Neolithic period of a sort of
Math
masculine sky god and a feminine
Earth goddess, right, but that's that Earth goddess that gets added
So it's here where we start moving and they take that first step toward a multiplicity of gods
Right is is takes place within the neolithic revolution and the move to
to settlements and then once you have
settled life right once you have
settled life, this can then give rise to all kinds of spirits and cultic deities, meaning
spirits and lesser sort of quote unquote deities that you can invoke, get to do favors,
bribe with different things, right?
That will cover different aspects of of settled life.
Once you start having villages and then eventually towns and eventually cities, yeah, you start
to get this
multitude of gods and spirits, even in an individual place.
Yeah, because if that particular place becomes important to you now, because you live
there, which in nomadic societies, you don't.
If you live there and you have the sense of, okay, this deity is associated with this
place, then you start to form these kinds of relationships.
Right.
And we see that with the development of sacred sites, right?
the many of the first of which are fountains springs of water because obviously you need water to live
hunter-gatherers due to but but when people go to settle they start to settle at the sacred sites
right they don't settle in a place for some kind of materialistic reasons and then sort of
spiritualize some elements of that place.
Yeah, and.
One of the ways that we know that this is the case is that there are these settlements in places that make no sense in terms of natural resources or whatever.
Right.
And we're going to start talking about particular settlements.
The most ancient settlements we've found and that we know of.
And what you find in those settlements is that the ritual elements like megalithic zone structures
that clearly have a religious...
purpose. Those are there before the homes, the residences, the dwellings are. And before
the agricultural projects start. So the sites are sites that are found and encountered
by nomadic peoples. And then when the time comes for the nomadic people to settle down,
they settle down at...
these sites. So they find a spring of water, there's a spirit that they associate with that spring of
water. Right. They form a settlement there. The spirit they had associated with the spring of water
now becomes one of the gods of that people. Right. They start to worship it. Right. And we talked
about this in terms of what happens after Bable and the fact that there are.
and gel experience, right, associated with these different things, right?
But the problem is humans are now starting to worship them as gods, right, in and of themselves.
So, going to the earliest settlements we have, right?
So, one of the earliest sites we have that's become semi-famous,
the same as those sometimes weird things are said about it, is go back to the tab.
Yeah, which we've mentioned on the show a few times before.
Yeah. I think it was way back in the log ago time though.
But like the year 2000.
Why go go back to the TEPI was was seems to have first been settled around 91 30 BC.
Again, I think there's not that old just accordingly, right?
But that's the tradition.
standard sort of dating. It's near the Syrian border with Turkey. And the main feature
there, the thing that gets everybody excited are these massive megaliths. They're these
huge regalithic stones with animal forms carved into them.
And they are arranged.
It is an even more, is it even more ancient stonehenge, but with these elaborate carvings
that Stonehenge lacks, which stonehenge stones are just propped up.
I know firsthand are just propped up.
Right.
And people, if you want to see what those stones that go backly, Tepi, look like, you could
just just google it up and have a look.
what they look like.
Right. And they are arranged in a way somewhat similar to what's going on with Stonehenge
in that most people agree now that they were used for astrological observation. Right?
But the stodes were put in place for the purpose of, and in some way the ritual carvings
are connected to constellations and things that would be at certain points during certain times of the year.
getting into super detail, there are people trying to get into super detail on that, in
the sense of exactly where what constellations were, like in 9 new 130 BC and stuff, and
that period.
But that is actually really hard to do, especially going back that far because the earth kind of
wobbles in its orbit. So things shift slightly.
The stars are not in the same place they were 5,000 years ago, right, let alone 10 relative
to any given position on Earth.
So but it's a general agreement that that's there.
But again, those megalithic structures were there before anything else that has been found
there.
which suggests that these were built as this spiritual site, right, as this site of religious ritual and sacrifice,
to which nomadic peoples would come at a certain time of year.
And then at a certain point, a certain later point after these way of structures were built,
then we find other like domestic housing units.
Right, for lack of a male term, domaziles.
We find evidence of human settlement there a little later.
Right, so then at a certain point people start to settle there at the spiritual site
permanently rather than just migrate there at certain times of year for ritual purposes,
religious purposes.
And this is true of all of these early
sites that we found that we're going to talk about now. The ritual site in every case
is there first. And exists is a place that people make what we would call a pilgrimage to.
And then only later do people settle around it on a permanent basis.
This is something that not only happened during the Neolithic Revolution.
This has happened throughout human history with sacred sites.
Right, where towns, villages, and things will grow up around certain sacred sites.
So there are two more very early sites.
them is Jericho, like the city of Jericho that's in Joshua. The city of Jericho, there's
been a human settlement there since circa 10,000 BC. Again, just accordingly, but that's
a big circa because rather infamously, the site of Jericho was kind of ruined by bad
archaeology. Dang it, bad archaeology.
There was a certain period of European archaeology,
where they got access to especially sites
of the Holy Land that had some biblical significance.
And there was a rush by dabblers with some money,
especially among the British,
to get down there and say,
now we can prove that the Bible is true
and being non-gift.
They wrecked a few sites and Jericho is infamously one of them.
They just started digging trenches and stuff.
In ancient Jericho.
And so that's made it really hard.
Just about anything you see about Jericho is super provisional.
And for the record, if you see anyone saying anything definitive about the archaeological site
of Jericho on either side.
Have you seen someone saying,
definitively, there's no way that Jericho was destroyed in the time of Joshua whenever they think that was
Be leery because the sites of mess you can't prove that
But also if they say oh no for sure
The city of Jericho was destroyed at the time of Joshua whenever they think that was they're also
Playing fast and loose right now the site's kind of a mess
So we can't learn as much from that as we might from some of these others that
to discover. But the other one we're going to talk about a little more is Chetelhoek,
which is from circa, again, 7,100 BC, again, just accordingly. So this one is a little
further on by a little, I mean a couple thousand years, then go backly Tepey, but is a more
advanced site. Right and it's a sort of fully developed...
site. Now when I say fully developed again, we're not talking about even a Sumerian city,
but there are clear individual resident family residences there where you can lay the floor
plan like we understand where people lived. The religious site is more developed. So progress
has been made in terms of human settlement by this point. But it also gives us a window
into sort of a...
couple other aspects of religion, right, in the Neolithic Revolution. One of those is
that we have burial sites. So at Chetelhoek, in the individual family residences, the
burial sites are in the floor, right? So there's a dirt floor, and the departed family
members were buried in
in the in the floor, right, in the in the family's domicile.
And they were buried with some things, right.
They were buried with things like food and extra clothing.
Yeah, which suggests, hey, you're gonna need this
in the afterlife that we could really have some concept of.
Right, so they had some concept of some kind of afterlife,
because otherwise why would they...
Why wouldn't they keep those things because they would need them not the dead person? Yeah, not able stuff
and
there were also
animal remains
and not of pet animals of sacrificial animals
Which implies that there were sacrifices being offered
in conjunction with the burial
Right.
which again further suggests the idea of an afterlife and the involvement of
spirits because
again why would you offer a sacrifice for a dead person
if they're dead and gone.
The other major element is that there are
individual shrines inside these family homes
And these individual shrines take the form of bullheads and sets of bull horns.
Not bullhorn like you yell through while you're picketing outside Walgreens.
Like the horns of a bull. Like you put on the front of your car if you live in Dallas.
Yeah, I'm told they all have that in Dallas.
Yes. Yes.
Because of the long horns. They're advanced.
Those are Aggies, that didn't boss.
have that in the dukes of hazard?
I think so. I think Jerry you
ing did too. Yeah.
They're actually illegal in most
of Texas, but they're not so
good if you're in a car accident.
But so there are these these
bold representations in the
shrines within the home, right?
And we know there's shrines
because there's evidence of
burning incense and sacrificial
offerings, which in
You
implies, right, there's family worship going on, and that is connected to a bullfinger,
right? And by the time we get writing, as soon as we get writing, which is sometime after
this, but you immediately see bulls everywhere, right? Particularly in terms of your sky or
your storm. The sky God becomes a storm god when rain.
becomes important for growing crops. Right? And you can see Hesse had records this transition.
He has the memory of this transition because he's got that extra layer of Gaia and Uranus,
right? The heavens and the earth, right? As being sort of that first phase of divinity. And then
Then you get cronos of the tight.
then you get Zeus the storm god. And that's he's kind of encapsulating some religious history there in his
version of the succession myth, the double succession there.
So we immediately find you know the bowl of heaven and the epic of Gilgamesh,
bowl, bail,
right, all of this, right, bowl,
symbolism gets carried on so we know.
goes back to this period and then there's also sort of that is the masculine. Then you find,
for example, go back to the tepis, some of the animal forms are fish and sea creatures, you find
the sort of sea serpent. So we've talked about behemoth and Leviathan, right, Mahaymot and Lothan,
right, the sort of toxic masculinity and toxic femininity of ancient paganism.
But at this very early tier of pagan religion.
Leviathan and Lotta as sort of this symbol of order and power and strength and virility
and Lotta and Leviathan, the C-Surpate chaos, destruction, disorder.
We see this reflected even in these sort of earliest sites.
And so through this process of people settling in places.
We get the beginnings of paganism as we would talk about paganism today.
Yeah, people worshiping gods.
Yeah, the kind of paganism that was practiced everywhere from India to Egypt to Greece, right?
That kind of paganism that got refined in the Axial Age that we were talking about.
But that step emerges out of the Neolithic revolution and people beginning to settle.
Right. And if you compare, right, we, this is a question we get a lot because we talk about how
pagan, that kind of paganism is kind of ubiquitous in the world. Yeah. And so some people say,
well, hold on, wait a minute. Yeah. What about like Native Americans with their sort of semi-monotheistic
belief in a great spirit? Right. Associated with the sky. Yeah. And I mean, some people will say,
What is
That means that these people were worshiping Yahweh and never fell into paganism.
Not exactly.
Yeah.
Right.
Or certain Pacific Islanders, right, other indigenous Islanders, similarly, right.
Couple things.
looking at, say, North and Central America, right?
We could probably throw in South America.
When you look at the cultures that had made the Neolithic Revolution, who had built cities,
it had stoneworking technology.
That's why it's called the Stone Age because we were using stone tools, as opposed to
the Bronze Age or the Iron Age.
you look at them, they all fell into, you know, you look at the ink.
you look at the Mayans, you look at the Aztecs, they basically fell into the same kind of patterns
of paganism as everybody else. Right? The groups that maintained more of the earlier view are the
ones that remained closer to the hunter-gatherer way of life. Yeah. Right? So that particular shift
didn't happen.
them. But even though we're not going to say that the sky spirit that's that we're talking about
is identical to Yahweh, the God of Israel, that is closer. That kind of religion is closer to
the religion of, say, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, then paganism is. They're a lot closer than the
the Aztecs, right?
Like.
And so...
This movement that happens
Right from
The religious movement from the religion of hunter-gatherers to the religion of the settled to paganism
represents a sort of religious falling away
Right, it is a negative religious development from the perspective of the true God, right
into the worship of many creatures.
essentially, right? As opposed to most beneficently what we can call those other holdovers is sort
of a half forgotten memory of the Trugod, right? Yeah.
But there's still this memory of this most I got out there. And there are reports from Christian
missionaries who went to some of those groups. Of exactly that, right? They kind of approached it.
way Saint Paul did the unknown God, right? Like you know, that kind of most
I God, that father God, who you have this idea is was out there
somewhere. Yeah, let me tell you about him. And also it should be
it should be noted that it's not easy to figure out exactly what some
of these groups practiced and believed prior to their contact with
right European Christians because frankly you know there's often no
literacy, you know, and and and they were mostly dead from disease. Yeah, mostly dead. And there's
some indications that there's a transformation that occurred with the contact with Christianity.
And so yeah, there's not any kind of and many cases are true pre-Christian, a truly pre-Christian
image of what they were doing. Right. Right. So what was the point of this episode?
I don't know. I think it's something to talk about. Yeah, what's the point, Uncle?
Why, Father Stephen? Why? I know. Almost three hours of my life once again.
That's that you'll never get back. No.
So the point is, the point is this. Right. The point is this.
We need to...
end up being my final thoughts again. I may be fiddling with our whole, fiddling with
our whole schema here. We're getting close to episode 100 ready to flip every app,
set a packet all in. Yeah. So, yeah, this will probably end up being my final. Let's
do. But so what's the point? Well, so the point is, the point is in our understanding
of religion. Right, understanding of religion.
We need to be a little more nuanced than we typically have been.
Because humanity was around for a long time before even the Torah was written.
And we know from the Torah that God was active during that time.
and God was active throughout.
Right, the period when the Torah, as we talked about, the collar was supposed to be read but wasn't being read.
And God was active throughout the second temple period.
God was active. And of course he has been active through all of subsequent Christian history.
Right.
But we tend to have...
This kind of weird idea that like before God talked to Moses,
like he'd been forgotten about. Right?
Or we've so cast our idea of religion in general around our particular
variety of Christianity, whatever that might be, whether it's Orthodox Christianity
or something else, uh, that we're like, well,
I mean how would a hunter gather?
have gotten saved.
Right.
Hunter gathered and have sacraments.
You know, like just the question itself is kind of amazing.
Yeah.
Like, Hunter gathered and have sacraments, right?
Like generations of people, right?
Oh, let's write.
What we're talking about when we say Orthodox Christianity.
Right.
Well, I need to define...
Orthodox Christianity is the right worship of the true God. And what that means in a certain
sense is that anywhere in the history of the world and of humanity where the right worship
of the true God has taken place.
We could say that was Orthodox Christianity.
When we on the Sunday of the triumph of Orthodoxy, I'd like to say we're not being triumphalistic,
but it's called the Sunday of the triumph of Orthodoxy, so we got to own it.
When we say we read the creed together that I see no consent, no potent creed, and we
say this is the faith on which the world was founded.
We're not making the claim that...
19th century German Lutherans made.
We're not saying, finally through the long scrabble of human history,
we have arrived at Orthodox Christianity of the tight practice in my parish.
And so the Louisiana in the 21st century,
which is the pinnacle of all human religion,
and all those benigned fools in the past didn't know what they were talking about
and didn't know who God was.
We're making almost the exact opposite claim.
We're claiming that what we're doing in the right worship of God,
and what St. Nicholas the Confessor of Constantinople was doing in the early
9th century, and what St. Paul was doing in Corinth when he lived there,
when he was leading.
And...
What Ezra was doing after the exile and what David was doing and what Moses and Aaron were doing and what Abraham was doing and what those people in the genealogies of Abraham and Seth were doing.
And what all the people
whose names we will never know in all those generations passed in pre-history were doing,
when they rightly worship the true God is all the same thing.
It's all the same thing.
There are things that we know about God now that they wouldn't have been able to articulate
then because God hadn't revealed them yet.
Right? So yes, nobody was saying the nice scene creed at Chitalhoiak in 6850 BC. But if there
was anyone there, and probably not at Chitalhoiak because it was a pagan site, but if there
There was anyone who passed through there.
Who, like Melchizedek or J-
the ethyro, and maintained the correct worship of the true God.
Then the God who that person came to know through sacrifice and prayer is the same God
we come to know through the liturgy, through the sacraments, through the Scriptures. It's the same God.
Right?
That God is the same three persons then is now.
And so it is fundamentally the same religion.
Not the pagans, but those who truly worship the true God throughout all the ages.
It's all the same religion.
And there are these transitions as texts are written and texts are recognized.
And texts take a place, the reading of texts takes a place in worship.
But that doesn't mean it's a different God.
And the fundamentals of worship of sacrifice and of prayer and of the offering of insets
haven't changed.
The same God being truly worshiped by humans who are the same kind of humans.
Just over time, as our human way of...
life has shifted. There have been shifts to it. As we've migrated, as we've multiplied.
So we've gone different places and had different experiences. Right? It's taken on
different shapes. But if it's the right worship of the true God, then it's the same.
And as we've always posited on this show, and I'm not embarrassed of, I believe that one
religion is Orthodox Christianity.
Because that's the God who it is.
That's the God who it is who is the same yesterday, today and forever.
So that's both my why this episode and my final thoughts as I mess with the episode structure.
Yeah, I think, you know, just to extend a little bit what you just said.
I think especially here in 2024, where a lot of us are trying to muddle our way around
in a societal level meaning crisis.
One of the big temptations is to like super left brain at all.
the precise
exact formulaic approach to x, y, and z, so I can get this right.
And it's ironically, even though we tend to think of this kind of thinking as sort of scientific.
Ironically, it's actually very magical kind of thinking.
And if you look at what the scriptures say about what it means to
worship the one true God. There are ultimately consistent if you understand it correctly, but varying
approaches to that over time. For instance, everything you see in Leviticus does not all carry forward
into the new covenant.
So it's just clearly something different going on.
But it is...
as you just said father, it is consistent, it is the same religion, even though the practices
have a transformation. And with this kind of absolutizing of formulae that gives a lot
of a sense of, I think it feels safe you know, like it's like well the world is nutty
and so you know give me the straight dope here so I can get this exactly right because I want
get it.
right because I'm tired of all the wrong. What you do is you end up absolutizing stuff that,
in some cases, is not supposed to be absolutized or
was appropriate for particular time and place and may not necessarily be appropriate for now. For
instance, God does not command us to offer up goats on altars now. Right? I don't think anyone
Cheers.
is doing that now, but I'm sure somebody is actually probably. But most people are not
saying that's what we should do. But nonetheless, there can be this kind of, again, this
formulaic approach to religion. And we absolutize things that can be variable, and we often
variableize things or vary things that should actually be absolute. And the point, the point
is to know and to worship the one.
true God, Father, Son and Holy Spirit, and not to worship these other gods. That's the point.
And even though the exact shape that that takes over time can alter, the point is to orient ourselves
towards Him. And this absolutizing impulse is, frankly, an impulse towards idolatry. And it's
and it's an idol tree of our concepts of
about God. Now by saying that I am and by no means nullifying the dogmatic inheritance
of the church or anything like that, but sometimes people take the dogmas that speak
about who God is and they worship them instead of God himself. Right? That's what I mean.
And one of the ways we could see we're falling into that or at least having a temptation
towards that.
is if we spend more time, frankly, and more energy
on our concepts about God,
then we do on the actual practices of worshiping Him
and praying to Him.
Because a lot of people have been saved,
a lot of people have been saved,
who were faithful to God,
but had very maybe even incorrect
or primitive concepts about...
him. A lot of people have been saved that way because they were faithful and did the things
that they were supposed to be doing. But a lot of people, frankly, are going to have some
answering to give in the life of the age to come, who spent a lot of time absolutizing
particular pictures of God and not actually following His commandments. Right? And so,
you know, one of our...
big themes for this podcast.
For the last four years now, and hundreds of hours now, has been, if you love God, you
will keep His commandments as it says many, many times in the scriptures.
And I think that looking at this kind of massive arc of human history and seeing how there
is this variance over time, there is these changes over time.
Underlines this, right, because the whole point is to approach the one true God and to worship
him.
the whole point.
to have that fundamental orientation and to follow through and to do the things that you're supposed to do.
Not just to say it, not just to honor him with your lips as it says in scripture, but actually to do it.
To be faithful. If you love him, you keep his commandments.
So this is just another angle from which to make that point.
And another, and in this particular case, to make the point as we have made many times,
times that there is
is incredible consistency between Old and New Testaments, but even to say that there
is this consistency within the arc of human history that forms the context of the Old and
New Testaments.
Again, this doesn't mean that you can say or do whatever religiously, and it's all fine.
That is not the point that's being made at all.
rather than those who are truly worshiping the true God.
Are truly worshiping the true God.
worshiping the true God, even if the particulars of the way that they do that and the particulars
of the way that they theologize about that show some development over time.
So well next time we're going to, as I said, be our 100th episode, our 4th anniversary.
So I hope you'll join us.
But that is our show for tonight.
So thank you for listening everyone.
If you didn't speak with us live, we'd like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritsNhVate.com.
You can soulful send us a message at our Facebook page.
As a voicemail, speakpipe.com slash sort of spirits.
And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need help in finding a
parish, head over to Orthodoxintro.org.
Enjoy this or a live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 pm
Eastern 4 pm Pacific.
I like the way you're walking if you're walking my way.
I'm that red bull.
Now let's fly away.
If you're on Facebook you can follow our page.
You can join our discussion group and give us reviews and ratings and share this show
with a friend.
And finally be sure to go to www.engshanfaith.com
Stoke Support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
I see me with her, no Stevie Wonder.
She don't ever wonder because she knows she's bad.
And I got her.
Grocery bag.
Thank you. Good night.
God bless you.
You've been listening.
to the Lord of Spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young,
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne, and the beasts, and the elders,
and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000,
and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land
that was slain to receive power, and riches,
and wisdom and strength and all.
honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.